<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The great interest of states &amp; kingdomes. A sermon preached before the Honorable House of Commons, at their late solemne fast, Feb. 25. 1645. / By Tho: Goodwin, B.D. one of the Assembly of Divines.</title>
            <author>Goodwin, Thomas, 1600-1680.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 128 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85436</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G1246A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E325_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200620</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861321</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861321</idno>
            <idno type="VID">159563</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85436)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 159563)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 53:E325[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The great interest of states &amp; kingdomes. A sermon preached before the Honorable House of Commons, at their late solemne fast, Feb. 25. 1645. / By Tho: Goodwin, B.D. one of the Assembly of Divines.</title>
                  <author>Goodwin, Thomas, 1600-1680.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 59, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Dawlman.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M DC XLVI. [1646]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Order to print at foot of page 59.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms CV, 14-15 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Religion and state --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Fast-day sermons --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-11</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:159563:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE GREAT
INTEREST
OF
States &amp; Kingdomes.</p>
            <p>A SERMON Preached before the
Honorable Houſe of <hi>COMMONS,</hi>
At their Late Solemne FAST,
<hi>Feb.</hi> 25. 1645.</p>
            <p>By <hi>THO: GOODWIN, B. D.</hi> One
of the Aſſembly of Divines.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>REVEL. 17. 14.</bibl>
               <p>Theſe ſhall make war with the Lamb, and the Lamb ſhall <hi>over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come</hi>
them: <hi>For</hi> he is the Lord of Lords, and King of Kings,
and they that are with him, are called, and choſen, and faithfull.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi>
Printed for R. DAWLMAN.
<hi>M DC XLVI.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:159563:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:159563:2"/>
            <head>To the Honourable Houſe of
COMMONS,
Aſſembled in PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Here preſent you with one piece of the
<hi>Counſels of God,</hi> next thoſe of his
diſpoſing the <hi>eternall</hi> conditions of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
of all other the greateſt, as which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerneth
the <hi>temporall ſalvation</hi> or <hi>deſtruction</hi>
of Kingdomes and Nations, which next to his <hi>Saints</hi>
therein, are deareſt to God, as his patience towards
them ſhews. A ſubject, which had it been ſet out accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
to the merit of it, would of it ſelf have faln at
your feet, who are the <hi>Repreſentative</hi> Body of this
Nation and Kingdom, and entitled it ſelfe to no other
Dedication then to you. But Providence having
brought it forth in the way of an ordinance of God,
<hi>preaching,</hi> in your eares, (though rudely) and you
having beene pleaſed to owne it, it is become yours by
all ſorts of Intereſt.</p>
            <p>It is certaine, that God did not bring that laſt and
fatall deſolation upon the Iews, untill all ſtates and
ranks of men amongst them had conſpired againſt the
Lord and <hi>his Anointed,</hi> and his followers: nor did
<pb facs="tcp:159563:3"/>
he bring upon them that their firſt captivity, untill all
ſorts had corrupted themſelves, the <hi>great men</hi> had
<hi>broken the yoke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 5.</note> the <hi>Prophet prophecyed
falſly,</hi> the <hi>Prieſts did bear rule by their means,</hi>
and <hi>the people loved to have it ſo:</hi> and then as
the Prophet addes, <hi>What will you do in the end
thereof?</hi> And yet therein God did not regard ſo
much what the People, as what their Rulers did.
<hi>I ſaid,</hi> (ſpeaking of the people) <hi>Surely theſe
are poore,</hi>
               <note place="margin">ver. 4,</note> 
               <hi>theſe are fooliſh, I will get me
to the GREAT men, but THESE have
ALL TOGETHER broke the yoke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">5.</note> 
               <hi>and burſt
the bands.</hi> Our comfort therefore is, we cannot be
undone without you, nor you without failing in this,
which is our <hi>GREATEST INTEREST.</hi> An Errour,
which if this Kingdome ſhould after ſo much bleeding
erre a ſecond time, is like hereafter never to be men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.
Your <hi>preſervation</hi> and <hi>guidance</hi> in this, is,
above all other, the conſtant and daily prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt<lb/>
humble ſervant,<lb/>
THO: GOODWIN.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:159563:3"/>
            <head>THE
INTEREST
OF
ENGLAND.</head>
            <head>A Sermon preached at the late Faſt,
before the Commons Houſe of
PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>PSAL. 105. 14, 14.</bibl>
                  <p>He ſuffered no man to doe them wrong: yea, he reproved
Kings for their ſakes:
Saying, Touch not mine anointed.—</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He words I have read, and thoſe
from the 10. <hi>verſe,</hi> as they hold
forth the firſt rearing of the
Church of the Jews in <hi>Abraham</hi>
and the Patriarchs; ſo, they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
as the firſt Primitive In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance
and Originall patterne of
Gods care and protection over his people in all A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges;
and likewiſe of his proceedings with all <hi>States</hi>
and <hi>Kingdomes,</hi> according unto their dealings with
his people, where ever caſt among them, to the end of
the world: exemplified in what was done for their
ſakes, and towards them and their Families.</p>
            <p>The Storie it ſelfe of <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi>
which theſe words refer to, and how God <hi>reproved
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:159563:4"/>
Abimelech</hi> King of <hi>Gerar,</hi> and <hi>Pharaoh</hi> King of <hi>Egypt,</hi>
and others <hi>for their ſakes,</hi> you may reade in the 12, 20,
and 26. Chapters of <hi>Geneſis;</hi> and of commands given
forth concerning them <hi>to doe them no wrong,</hi> yea not to
<hi>touch</hi> them;<note place="margin">Gen. 20. 7.</note> declaring alſo of <hi>Abraham,</hi> that he was a
<hi>Prophet,</hi> and ſo not to be injured: Onely what in the
Story is uttered ſcatteredly and in ſeverall places, is
by the Prophet <hi>David</hi> ſummarily put together, <hi>Touch
not mine anointed, and doe my Prophets no harme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is a Controverſie upon theſe words, <hi>Touch
not mine anointed,</hi> that they ſhould be intended princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally
of <hi>Kings,</hi> and of theſe Patriarchs, as under the
notion of <hi>Kings.</hi> I ſhall but clear it in a word.</p>
            <p>Whether theſe Patriarchs were Kings or no, I will
not now diſpute; <hi>Abraham</hi> is called <hi>a mighty Prince</hi>
by the children of <hi>Heth, Gen.</hi> 23. 6. yet however here
the holy Ghoſt ſpeaks of <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> as
repreſenting the people of Iſrael; and his ſcope is to
ſhew Gods care and protection of his people by their
example, which is cleare, 1. by all the current
and ſtreame of the whole Pſalme; all that goes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
and which followes after, is wholly to ſhew his
care of the people of Iſrael from firſt to laſt. But as for
Kings, or Gods care over them as ſuch, we may ſay as
<hi>Paul</hi> in another caſe,<note place="margin">Heb. 7. 14.</note> 
               <hi>Of that Tribe the holy Ghoſt ſpeaks no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,</hi>
that is, in this <hi>Pſa</hi> nothing as touching <hi>Monarchie,</hi>
(as he there ſayes nothing as <hi>concerning the Prieſthood.</hi>)</p>
            <p>And 2. then the words in the 12. verſe, which ſpeak
of the perſons of theſe Patriarchs, <hi>when they were but a
few men in number,</hi> yea, <hi>very few,</hi> refer not to Kings, nor
unto theſe Patriarchs as ſuch, for he ſpeaks of their
whole families, their wives, children and ſervants:
Yea, theſe three Patriarchs, <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:159563:4"/>
they were all alive at once; <hi>Iſaac</hi> was above 70.
years old, afore <hi>Abraham</hi> dyed, and <hi>Jacob</hi> 15. and
but one of theſe could have been King at once, and
yet you ſee he ſpeaks of them all complexedly, and
as making a company together, when <hi>they were few,</hi>
and <hi>very few,</hi> he ſaid, <hi>Touch not mine anointed,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea 3. It is ſo farre from being meant of them as
Kings, that it is expreſly ſaid in the words of the
Text, <hi>He reproved Kings for their ſakes,</hi> therein ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
of them as of a ſort of people diſtinct from
Kings, and yet of a higher and dearer value with
God, then thoſe Kings reproved for them.</p>
            <p>But it will be ſaid, that if it ſhould not be meant of
them under the relation of Kings, yet however as of
perſons extraordinary, and therefore this charge
and inſtance cannot be drawne into a pattern of Gods
care and protection over all Saints, and the people of
God, which is the ſcope which I have put up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
the words.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, that though indeed their perſons were
extraordinary, yet here they are withall ſet forth
as repreſenting the people of God, whom they
were the fathers of. It is cleare by the eighth <hi>verſo;
He hath remembred his Covenant for ever, the word which
he commanded to a thouſand generations:</hi> The perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance
of which Covenant, to confirme the truth of
it, he exemplifies by the ſtory of Gods providence
over theſe. What therefore he ſaith of theſe <hi>anointed</hi>
ones here, it extendeth to a <hi>thouſand generations</hi> to
come: and as <hi>Abraham</hi> in other things was a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
perſon, <hi>in faith juſtifying</hi> he is made ſuch, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.
<hi>In faith</hi> as <hi>ſanctifying, Jam.</hi> 2. In being <hi>heire of the
world, Rom.</hi> 4. 13. ſo is he here alſo: and <hi>Iſaac</hi> and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:159563:5"/>
               <hi>Jacob</hi> with him in their anointing.</p>
            <p>But you will yet ſay, It is true, they may be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood
as Common perſons, repreſenting indeed the
Nation of the Jews; but yet will what is here ſaid,
be warrantably extended to the Beleevers of Jewes
and Gentiles under the New Teſtament to the end
of the world?</p>
            <p>I anſwer, Yes; For the Covenant that God
made with <hi>Abraham,</hi> was to be <hi>heire of the world,</hi> as
well as <hi>heire of Canaan;</hi> ſo <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 13. And accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly
in other things the Analogie holds for
them with theſe here: For as theſe, ſo the Saints,
they are called <hi>Strangers and Pilgrims,</hi> ſcattered and
diſperſed in all Nations; So <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaks of them;
even as here he calls theſe <hi>ſtrangers, ver.</hi> 12. when
they were but <hi>few in number,</hi> and <hi>ſtrangers in the
land,</hi> as the Saints in the world. To give parallel
places of Scripture, to ſtrengthen this. In the
Old Teſtament. In the forty fift Pſalme, you
have a Propheſie of the Church of the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
under the type of <hi>Solomon,</hi> taking <hi>Pharoahs</hi>
daughter, who was a Gentile, into his bed, as
<hi>Chriſt,</hi> of whom he was the Type, one day ſhould
doe the Gentiles: which Church is made that great
mother that ſhall have ſuch multitudes of children,
<hi>Gal.</hi> 4. Now of thoſe children, of the Church of the
New Teſtament as the Mother, and of Chriſt as the
Father, the 16. verſe of that Pſalme thus ſpeaks,
<hi>Inſtead of</hi> THY FATHERS <hi>ſhall be</hi> THY CHILDREN,
<hi>whom thou mayſt make Princes in all the earth.</hi> The mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
whereof is this, that in the ſtead of theſe great
Patriarchs, and other the Fathers of the Jews, (ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
of in the Text) ſhall ſucceed others, the children
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:159563:5"/>
of the New Teſtament, even all the Saints, as Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors
of them; and as they were as Princes in all
Lands they came into, here, <hi>ſo ſhall thy children be,</hi>
ſayes the Pſalmiſt there. And the 7. verſe of that
Pſalme calls them <hi>anointed,</hi> and ſo ſpeaks alſo in the
language of the Text, when under that notion he
commands not to <hi>touch</hi> them; That verſe ſpeaking of
Chriſt, ſaith, <hi>He is</hi> ANOINTED <hi>with the oyle of glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
above his</hi> FELLOWES: namely, theſe his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes
and <hi>children,</hi> ſpoken of ver. 16. you have at
once, as the great <hi>anointed</hi> one, Chriſt, ſo all his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
called <hi>anointed</hi> ones alſo: and as they are his
<hi>fellowes,</hi> ſo <hi>anointed</hi> too. Thus you have all meet:
<hi>Abraham</hi> and the Fathers, the anointed ones of the
Old Teſtament, Chriſt and his Saints the anointed
ones in the New, in their ſtead; and both Princes and
Strangers in all Lands; and ſo of the one as well as
the other this charge is here intended, <hi>Touch not mine
anointed, &amp;c.</hi> And to this accords the language of the
New Teſtament, the whole myſticall body is called
<hi>Chriſt, 1 Cor.</hi> 12. 12. and Beleevers his fellows are
ſaid to <hi>have received an anointing, 2 Cor. 1. 21. 1 John</hi>
2. 27. yea and elſewhere the reaſon of this their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation,
and Gods protection over them, is put
upon this very anointing,<note place="margin">Eſay 10. 27.</note> 
               <hi>The burthen ſhall be taken off
thy ſhoulder,</hi> (ſpeaking of the oppreſſion of Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple)
<hi>and the yoke ſhall be deſtroyed</hi> BECAUSE OF THE
ANOINTING.</p>
            <p>Having thus explained the words, I come to thoſe
Obſervations which I ſhall make out of them, and
inſiſt on at this time. I reſolve the words into theſe
three parts.</p>
            <p>1. Here is the <hi>neereneſſe and the dearneſſe of the Saints
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:159563:6"/>
unto God;</hi> They are dearer to him then Kings and
States, ſimply conſidered; that is, otherwiſe then
as they in their perſons are alſo Saints; for you ſee
that for their ſakes he reproved Kings, and ſo ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
that he preferreth them to Kings.</p>
            <p>2. Here is <hi>the great danger to Kings and States, to
deale with his Saints otherwiſe then well.</hi> Which appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth
many wayes: For he doth not onely in <hi>words</hi>
give a charge not to <hi>touch</hi> them, but he carryes it in
a high way, (for ſo God may doe when he pleads
their cauſe) <hi>Touch them not:</hi> as if he had ſaid, Let me
ſee if you dare ſo much as touch them: and it is with
an intimation of the higheſt threatning if they ſhould;
upon your perill, if you doe; for that is the ſcope of
ſuch a ſpeech: and accordingly in <hi>deeds</hi> he made
this good, for the Text ſaith, <hi>He ſuffered no man to doe
them wrong;</hi> Not that he did altogether prevent all
wrong and injuries, for they received many as they
went through thoſe lands; but at no time did he put
it up at their hands, or let it goe unpuniſht: in
that ſenſe he ſuffered them not. You know how he
plagued <hi>Pharaoh King of Egypt</hi> with great plagues, and
all his houſhold, for <hi>Abrahams</hi> wives ſake, <hi>Gen.</hi> 12.
And ſo <hi>Abimelech King of Gerar,</hi> the Lord commeth
upon him with a greatnes, and his firſt word is in <hi>Gen.</hi>
20. 3. <hi>Behold, than art but a dead man,</hi> afore he had firſt
told him why or wherefore; though then he addes
the reaſon; he brings him upon his knees, <hi>ver.</hi> 4. bids
him look to it, that he give ſatisfaction to <hi>Abraham,</hi>
and reſtore his wife to him againe, <hi>ver.</hi> 7. and well he
ſcap'd ſo; and tels him alſo that he muſt be behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den
to <hi>Abrahams</hi> prayers for his life; <hi>He is a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet,</hi>
ſaith he, <hi>and he ſhall pray for thee, and thou ſhalt
live.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:159563:6"/>
The third is the care and protection which God
had over them, ſet out and amplified 1. by the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
and condition of the perſons whom he defended:
though <hi>few,</hi> men of <hi>number,</hi> that is ſoone reckoned,
for their power and ſtrength, a few, or very ſmall,
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſo the Septuagint in the parallel place, 2 <hi>Chro.</hi>
16. 19. As alſo 2. by what he did for them, <hi>He ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
no man</hi> how great ſoever <hi>to doe them any wrong,</hi> how
ſmall ſoever; not without recompence and ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
not to <hi>doe it,</hi> though they had a mind to it, though
the people had an <hi>ill eye</hi> at them, <hi>Gen.</hi> 26. 11. God
cauſeth <hi>Abimelech</hi> to make a Law on purpoſe, <hi>Abime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lech
charged all his people</hi> in <hi>Iſaacs</hi> behalf, and of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily,
(which I mention, becauſe it gives light to the
Text) and ſpeaks in the very words of the Text, <hi>He
that</hi> TOUCHETH <hi>this man or his wife, ſhall be put to
death:</hi> although they <hi>envied him, ver. 14. ſtrived with
him, ver. 20. hated him, ver.</hi> 27.</p>
            <p>I ſhal paſſe over the ſett handling the firſt of theſe,
namely, <hi>The neerneſſe and dearneſſe of the Saints to God,</hi> it
will after come in well enough, under the ſecond,
as the reaſon thereof.</p>
            <p>That maine thing which I have ſingled forth to
inſiſt upon, is, <hi>the danger</hi> that is unto States, to deale
otherwiſe then well with the Saints, Gods anointed.
And the Obſervation is plainly this,</p>
            <p>That the dealing well or ill with the Saints of God,<note place="margin">Obſer.</note> it
is the greateſt and higheſt <hi>INTEREST</hi> of <hi>Kings</hi>
and <hi>Kingdomes,</hi> on which their welfare or their
ruine depends.</p>
            <p>I have the ſtory of the whole world afore me, to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:159563:7"/>
gleane Demonſtrations and inſtances out of, to
make good this truth. But I ſhall endeavour to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
it to you under that proſpect that runs through
the ſtory of the whole Bible. My Obſervation out
of the Story of which, and the ſumme and iſſue of all,
is this, <hi>That God from the beginning hath in his Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
ſo ordered it, that the greateſt and moſt flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
Kingdomes and States ſhould ſtill have to doe with
his Saints and People in all Ages, and either they have
beene broken by their ill uſing of them, or they have
proſpered by their well dealing with them.</hi> You ſhall
find this I ſay throughout the whole Scripture. My
Text leads the round to all the reſt, and I therefore
indeed choſe it rather then any other, though other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
as a bottome to this point, I might have pitcht
upon others perhaps more full.</p>
            <p>We will begin with the very firſt Kings and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes
that you read of after the Flood. How he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved
the <hi>King of Egypt,</hi> and the <hi>King of the Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines,</hi>
for the ſake of <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Iſaac,</hi> that I menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned
afore. Beſides thoſe there is mention of <hi>foure
Kings, Gen. 14. Amraphel</hi> King of <hi>Shinar</hi> or <hi>Babylon,</hi>
which was the firſt Kingdome in the world after the
flood, <hi>Gen.</hi> 10. 10. and was one of, yea the firſt great
Monarchie. There is likewiſe <hi>Chedorlaomer</hi> King of
<hi>Elam,</hi> or <hi>Perſia,</hi> which afterward likewiſe proved a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchie.
For as <hi>Aſſyria</hi> and <hi>Babylon</hi> made the firſt,
ſo you know <hi>Perſia</hi> was the next. You have two other
Kings more there confederate with theſe. Theſe
foure Kings they brake in upon,<note place="margin">Gyants.</note> and ſmote all the
Countries about; they ſmote the REPHAIMS in
<hi>Aſhteroth Karnaim,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Terrible ones.</note> and the <hi>ZUZIMS</hi> in <hi>Ham,</hi> and the
EMIMS,<note place="margin">Deut. 2. 10, 11.</note> and the <hi>Horites</hi> in <hi>Mount Seir, And they returned
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:159563:7"/>
and came to Enmiſhpat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on exemplified in all States and Kingdoms through the Scriptures.</note> 
               <hi>which is Cadeſh, and ſmote all the
Countrey of the</hi> AMALEKITES, <hi>and alſo the</hi> AMORITES,
<hi>that dwelt in Hazezon tamar,</hi> as you may reade, <hi>verſes</hi>
6, 7, 8. And all the while they over-ran theſe vaſt
Countries,<note place="margin">1. Foure Kings overthrowne by <hi>Abraham.</hi>
               </note> where there was not one Saint to be
found, they found no reſiſtance, having but to doe
with Nations, not Saints in them; but unhappily to
them, when they came to fight againſt the Kings of
<hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> they light upon one Saint, and
but one, and that is <hi>Lot,</hi> ſo the 12. <hi>verſe, They tooke
Lot, Abrahams brothers ſonne, (who dwelt in Sodome) and
his goods, and departed.</hi> Alas to them; little thought
they what a Priſoner they had: they took him in the
crowd amongſt the wickedeſt people under heaven,
a people ſo wicked, that one would have thought
God ſhould ſo little have conſidered this one Saint,
to ſave him from periſhing, as that his vengeance
ſhould have taken the opportunity to ruine theſe,
though this one poore <hi>Lot</hi> had been involved in their
deſtruction. But you ſhall ſee how tender God is of
his Saints.<note place="margin">Jerem. 3.</note> They had unawares <hi>devoured an hallowed
thing,</hi> one <hi>righteous Lot,</hi> and had taken him but Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner;
they had drunk poyſon, and all the riches, and
all the goods they had taken, they vomit up againe,
together with their owne blood. The Lord in this
giving demonſtration of that his care and skill which
<hi>Peter</hi> makes obſervation of upon the ſtory of <hi>Lot</hi> &amp; the
Sodomites, <hi>The Lord knowes how to</hi> PRESERVE <hi>the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous,
and</hi> RESERVE <hi>the unjuſt, 2 Pet.</hi> 2. 9. And whom
ſhould God uſe to be the inſtrument to doe this too?
God had not many more Saints then in the world, but
onely <hi>Melchiſedechs</hi> we reade of, and <hi>Abraham</hi> and
his family, and God uſeth that one <hi>Abraham;</hi> and he
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:159563:8"/>
had an Army but of a <hi>few,</hi> and a <hi>very few,</hi> (even as
the Text hath it) but <hi>three hundred and eighteene men,</hi>
borne in his houſe, <hi>ver.</hi> 14. he <hi>purſues</hi> them, and <hi>ſmites</hi>
them, <hi>ver.</hi> 17. with a great ſlaughter, and brought
back <hi>all the goods,</hi> and his brother <hi>Lot</hi> and his goods,
&amp;c.<note place="margin">Gen. 20. 16.</note> 
               <hi>ver.</hi> 18. And <hi>thus they were reproved.</hi> You ſee the
Text made good from the very firſt beginning of
Kingdomes, <hi>He reproved Kings for their ſakes</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed.</p>
            <p>Thus he began the world at firſt; and this very
victorie is made a leading caſe, a ſtanding encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
to the ſons of <hi>Abraham,</hi> the Saints, for ever af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.
So you have it applyed in <hi>Eſay 41. 2. Who raiſed
up</hi> (ſayes God, to raiſe up his peoples hearts) <hi>the</hi>
RIGHTEOUS MAN <hi>from the Eaſt?</hi> namely, this one
<hi>Abraham?</hi> and <hi>called him to his foot,</hi> Follow me, Ile be
thy Generall, ſaid God to him, <hi>Gave the Nations be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
him, and made him rule over Kings;</hi> he means theſe
very Kings you have heard the ſtory of: <hi>He gave
them as the duſt to his ſword, and as driven ſtubble to his
bow; he purſued them, and paſſed ſafely, &amp;c.</hi> Did God
doe thus then for one or two of his Saints, and will
he not goe on? What ſaith the 4. verſe? <hi>Who hath
wrought and done it, calling the generations from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning,</hi>
and ſo having ordained all the generations of
<hi>Abraham</hi> to do the like exploits in their ſeverall ages.
<hi>I the Lord am the firſt, and with the laſt, I am he.</hi> I began
to doe this with <hi>Abraham,</hi> and I will goe on to doe
ſo, even to the laſt, for the ſons of <hi>Abraham.</hi> And that
this is plainly his meaning, appeares by <hi>ver.</hi> 8. where
he makes a generall application of it to his ſeed, <hi>But
thou Iſrael, art my ſervant, Jacob whom I have choſen, the</hi>
SEED OF ABRAHAM <hi>my friend.</hi> Therefore
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:159563:8"/>
ſaith he, ver. 10. <hi>Feare thou not, (thou worme Jacob,
ver.</hi> 14.) <hi>for I am with thee: be not diſmayed, for I am
thy God: I will ſtrengthen thee, yea, I will help thee,
yea, I wil uphold thee with the right hand of my righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.
Behold, all they that were incenſed againſt thee,
ſhall be aſhamed and confounded: they ſhall be as nothing,
and they that ſtrive with thee ſhall periſh.</hi> All the whole
Chapter is nothing elſe but incouragement to all
the ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> from this very inſtance I have
now given you. And the Text here confirmes it,
premiſing unto all thoſe inſtances, <hi>He hath remembred
his Covenant, the word he commanded to a thouſand gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next Kingdome in the world that flouriſhed
in thoſe firſt times,<note place="margin">2. AEgypt.</note> that grew to any greatneſſe that
we reade of, was that of <hi>Egypt;</hi> and though <hi>Cham</hi> the
founder of <hi>Egypt</hi> was curſed, yet as uſually thoſe God
layes the greateſt curſe upon, he firſt begins to bleſſe
with outward bleſſings in the world; ſo he did the
ſeed of <hi>Cham,</hi> in that infancy of that new world.
How renowned a Kingdome that then was, both
for continued ſucceſſion of Kings in a race, (which
<hi>Eſay</hi> inſinuates) and for other greatneſſe,<note place="margin">Chap. 19. 11.</note> the ſtory
of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and <hi>Herodotus,</hi> and other prophane ſtories
do celebrate: it was as would ſeem in thoſe firſt times
more flouriſhing then <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> (the Territories of <hi>Aſſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria</hi>
could not then be great, when ſuch other three
Kings forementioned bordered about it, and when
<hi>Chedorlaomer</hi> of <hi>Perſia</hi> was the chief of all the foure)
Now ſee how ſtill the Lord doth follow on this his
great deſigne,<note place="margin">Gen. 14. 4, 5.</note> he will have his Saints to be caſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
this Kingdome, and to live therein; and not onely
<hi>Abraham,</hi> and <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> but in the end all their poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:159563:9"/>
Tis the next ſtory the Pſalmiſt gives inſtance of
to the purpoſe in hand, and let us take it, but as he
relates it: ſaith he, <hi>ver. 17. He ſent a man before
them, even Joſeph, who was ſold for a ſervant, whoſe
feet they hurt with fetters; (Potiphar</hi> onely did it, yet
God layes it upon the Nation) But as the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt
obſerves, the Lord was even with them for it;
<hi>ver. 21. &amp;</hi> 22. He made this man not onely <hi>Lord
of Pharaohs houſe,</hi> but he addes, <hi>to</hi> BINDE HIS
PRINCES <hi>at his pleaſure,</hi> as they before had done him.
As <hi>Abraham</hi> afore, ſo <hi>Joſeph</hi> now is another leading
inſtance, <hi>To</hi> BIND <hi>their</hi> KINGS <hi>with</hi> CHAINES, <hi>their
Nobles with fetters of iron,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Thou haſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved our lives, <hi>Gen.</hi> 47. 25.</note> 
               <hi>ſuch honour have</hi> ALL HIS
SAINTS, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 149. He made this man a Saviour to
them, (as themſelves acknowledge) and whilſt
they dealt well with him and his Brethren, <hi>as
he bleſſed Potiphars houſe for his ſake,</hi> ſo he bleſſed
the Prince and all Egypt alſo for his ſake. And
whilſt Egypt was the Nurſery, or rather the Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary
(as it was called anciently <hi>Horreum Romani
Imperii</hi>) to theſe <hi>anointed ones,</hi> the people of God,
ſo long it greatly flouriſhed. But <hi>verſ.</hi> 25. God
turned their heart <hi>to hate his people, and to deale
ſubtilly with his ſervants,</hi> (for malice and cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
alwayes goe together in oppreſſing the Saints)
and how they oppreſſed them, you all know. But as
he had reproved Kings for their ſakes afore, and <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raohs</hi>
Progenitors among the reſt, ſaying, <hi>Touch not
mine anointed,</hi> as here, ſo he begins with a meſſage by
<hi>Moſes</hi> his Ambaſſadour ſent to that King of Egypt, and
therein uſeth the ſame kind of language, <hi>Ex.</hi> 4. 22, 23.
<hi>Thou ſhalt ſay unto Pharaoh, Thus ſaith the Lord, Iſrael is my
ſon, even my firſt-born.</hi> There is only this difference in
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:159563:9"/>
the expreſſion; the Pſalmiſt here cals them his <hi>anoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed;</hi>
there, his <hi>firſt-borne.</hi> And it is as if he had ſaid, Tell
<hi>Pharaoh</hi> I <hi>Jehovah</hi> am a greater King then thou art,
and therefore my firſt-borne is greater then thy firſt-borne;
And <hi>Let my ſonne, my firſt borne goe, that he may
ſerve me;</hi> he carryes all high: <hi>And if thou refuſe to let
him goe, I will ſlay thy ſonne, even thy firſt-borne,</hi> and ſo
indeed he did in the end. They left not oppreſſing the
people of God (and the great quarrell was to let them
goe to worſhip) till ſuch time as God did overthrow
that Nation, with ſo great an overthrow, as no King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
could have a greater not totally to be deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed;
and indeed ſo great, as you heare no more of
them till <hi>Solomons</hi> time. There is not a word of <hi>Egypt</hi>
in all the time of <hi>Joſhua,</hi> and of the <hi>Judges,</hi> till you
reade of <hi>Solomons</hi> marrying <hi>Pharoahs</hi> daughter. Here
you ſee <hi>Egypt,</hi> both bleſſed while they dealt well
with the people of God, and broken when they dealt
ill with them.</p>
            <p>To let paſſe thoſe petty Kings of Canaan,<note place="margin">Aſſyria <hi>and</hi> Babylon.</note> over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
by <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Joſhua,</hi> let us come next to <hi>Aſſyria,</hi>
which together with <hi>Babylon</hi> is reckoned the firſt great
Monarchie. The <hi>beginning</hi> of the Aſſyrian Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie
<hi>being from Babylon, Gen.</hi> 10. 10. and the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
returning againe to <hi>Babel,</hi> both are juſtly rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned
but one, though in their ſeverall revolutions
they were diſtinct. This Monarchie in the Infancie
of it, <hi>Abraham</hi> had to doe with, and as you heard, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercame
the King thereof: <hi>Egypts</hi> King was alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved
for their ſakes, and <hi>Perſia,</hi> and two Kings
more: God ordering it, that the Father and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenter
of the faithfull ſhould reprove and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſe
thoſe Kings, whom his ſeed ſhould after ruine.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:159563:10"/>
How the people of God were oppreſſed, firſt by
the Aſſyrian kings, and then by the Babyloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,
the ſtory of the <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Chronicles</hi> doe
ſhew: The Aſſyrian often oppreſſing them, and at
laſt carrying the tenne Tribes captive, as Babylon
did the other two. Now to make ſhort worke of
both, you ſhall finde one Scripture, <hi>Jer.</hi> 50. where
you ſhall ſee them both put together in their ruine,
and the ruine of both put upon this, their oppreſſion
of the people of God. I mention that Scripture one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
becauſe it ſummarily containes the whole: <hi>ver.</hi> 17.
ſayes God, <hi>Iſrael is a ſcattered ſheep, the Lions have
driven him away:</hi> they were a ſcattered people: or as
<hi>Junius</hi> and <hi>Piſcator</hi> hath it, they were <hi>parva pecus,</hi> a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
flock, <hi>few,</hi> and <hi>very ſmall,</hi> in compariſon of the
Nations, as the Pſalmiſt hath it here: <hi>and the Lions
drave them away.</hi> Who were theſe Lions? <hi>Firſt,</hi> ſaith
hee, <hi>the King of Aſſyria hath devoured him,</hi> hee ſeized
as it were on the fleſh,<note place="margin">2 King. 15. 16, 20, 29. <hi>&amp; 16 7. &amp;</hi> 17. 3.</note> (<hi>Pul, Tiglath Pileſer,</hi> and
<hi>Salmanazar,</hi> oppreſſing and captivating them,
2 <hi>Kings</hi> 15.) and <hi>laſt This Nebuchad-nezzar King
of Babylon,</hi> (he ſpeaks of him with ſcorne and
indignation, <hi>This Nebuchadnezzar) hath broken the
bones:</hi> And becauſe that he came laſt, and took away
all, as a ſweeping raine, therefore his anger riſeth
moſt againſt him, <hi>Ver. 18. Thus ſaith the Lord of Hoſts,
Behold, I will puniſh the King of Babylon and his Land, as
I puniſhed the King of Aſſyria.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sulianus Anna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Tom. 4. An. Mund. 3333. &amp; An. 3452.</note> 
               <hi>Merodach</hi> of <hi>Babylon</hi> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued
the <hi>Aſſyrian, Nebuchadnezzer</hi> utterly ruines <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neve</hi>
the head City thereof, and then <hi>Babels</hi> time comes
to be waſted alſo, and the whole Land therewith.
Here is that Monarchy gone you ſee, both Aſſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian
and Babylonian, and whoſoever were the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:159563:10"/>
this was the cauſe from Gods owne mouth.
Adde unto which, that in the next Chapter. <hi>Jer.</hi> 51.
11. <hi>Becauſe</hi> (ſayes that Text) <hi>it was the vengeance of
the Lord, and of his Temple.</hi> And take in alſo <hi>verſ.</hi> 35.
<hi>The violence done to me, and to my fleſh, be upon Babilon,
ſhall the inhabitants of Zion ſay, and my blood upon the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants
of Caldea, ſhall Jeruſalem ſay,</hi> then when they
are deſtroyed.</p>
            <p>Now there are a great many other kingdomes and
Nations,<note place="margin">4. All the neighbouring Kingdomes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Judea.</hi>
               </note> that bordered about the Jewes, whom God
(as I remember) calleth his <hi>evill neighbors,</hi> for their ill
will to Zion: theſe all fell either by or with Babylon.
Of theſe you ſhall reade in the 25, 26, 27, and 28,
Chapters of <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> and ſo on: God there ſends
the cup round to all the Nations: All thoſe Nations
certainly had infinite provocations of Nationall ſins
of all ſorts, againſt God, amongſt them; but you ſhall
ſee ſtill God there layes his ſuit and quarrell againſt
them onely for their ill dealing with his people, to
whom they were neighbours round about.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He begins with the</hi> Ammonites,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Ammon.</hi>
               </note> Chap. 25. 2. <hi>and what
was her ſinne that ruined her?</hi> Ammon <hi>was but glad
at the fall of the Jewes.</hi> Behold (<hi>ſaith the 3. verſ.</hi>) thou
ſaidſt <hi>AHA,</hi> againſt my Sanctuary, when it was profaned, and
againſt the Land of Iſrael, when it was deſolate, and againſt
the Houſe of Judah, when they went into captivity, <hi>they did
not help it forward, only cryed Aha.</hi> Therefore, <hi>ſaith
God, v.</hi> 4. I wil deliver thee to the men of the Eaſt for a poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion;
<hi>and ver.</hi> 6. Becauſe (<hi>as in ſpeech (as afore) ſo in
geſture they expreſſed the like joy at it</hi>) thou haſt clap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped
thy hands, and ſtamped with the feet, and rejoyced in
heart, with all thy deſpight againſt the Land of Iſrael; Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold,
therefore, I will ſtretch out mine hand upon thee, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:159563:11"/>
will deliver thee for a ſpoyle to the Heathen, I will deſtroy
thee, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next that hee mentioneth is <hi>Moab.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Moab.</note> Shee
did but caſt out a word; ſo verſ. 8. She did but onely
ſay this, <hi>Behold, the Houſe of Judah is like unto all the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then,</hi>
now laid waſt as they, and there is no difference
in the protection of their God over them, more than
over the Heathen themſelves; it was but this word
caſt out: yet <hi>therefore</hi> ſaith the Lord, ver. 9. <hi>Behold I will
open the ſide of Moab:</hi> He would break through and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen
his ſtrong <hi>Frontier Cities,</hi> (as the next words ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain
it) break his ribs, &amp; ſo enter into his bowels; and
ver. 10. <hi>the Ammonites ſhall be no more remembred among
the Nations.</hi> No other ſin in mentioned, but this word,
about his people.</p>
            <p>He comes next to <hi>Edom,</hi>
               <note place="margin">3. Edom.</note> 
               <hi>ver.</hi> 12. who was the poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
of <hi>Eſau,</hi> and their brother, (as you ſhall hear anon)
and of them he ſaith, <hi>Becauſe that Edom hath dealt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
the houſe of Judah by taking vengeance, and greatly
offended, and revenged himſelfe upon him;</hi> THEREFORE
ſaith he, ver. 13. <hi>I will cut off man and beaſt from it, and
make it deſolate.</hi> He riſeth ſtill in his puniſhments pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable
to their ſins, and to their dealings with
his people. And I will doe it, ſayes he, <hi>by the hand of
my own people, ver.</hi> 14. that were oppreſſed by them.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Edom</hi> he carryes the cup to <hi>Philiſtia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">4. Philiſtia.</note> who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
they had an old grudge againſt the Iſraelites,
<hi>a deſpightfull heart to deſtroy them for the old hatred, ver.</hi>
15. THEREFORE <hi>I will execute great vengeance on
them, ver.</hi> 16, 17.</p>
            <p>In the next place,<note place="margin">5. Tyre.</note> he comes to <hi>Tyre,</hi> poore <hi>Tyre,</hi>
I call her ſo, becauſe as of all the Nations they were
the moſt ingenious in themſelves: (In ſo much as
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:159563:11"/>
Chriſt ſayes, <hi>They would have repented, &amp;c.</hi>) and moſt
ingenuous of all Nations elſe unto the Jewes, that
helped them to build the Temple, and were confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates
with <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Solomon.</hi> And what was her
fault? A meere temptation of love to her ſelfe, ſuch
as might befall any in the like caſe. Read <hi>Chap.</hi> 26. 2.
<hi>Son of man, becauſe Tyrus hath ſaid againſt Jeruſalem,
Aha, ſhe is broken that was the gates of the people,</hi> I SHALL
BE REPLENISHED <hi>now ſhe is laid waſte.</hi> The meaning
is this, I ſhall now have all the trade. You know
<hi>Tyre</hi> lay nigh to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and it was a place of the
greateſt trade and merchandiſe then in the world,
ſhe was the <hi>Mart of Nations,</hi> (ſo ſhe is called in <hi>Eſay</hi> 23.
and in <hi>Ezek.</hi> 27. 3.) and though ſhe had the greater
trade of the two already, yet ſhe rejoyced in this, that
<hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſhould be laid waſte, <hi>who had been the gates of
the people,</hi> whither much people came for traffique,
as well as to me. Now thinks ſhe (and it was but a
ſelfe-loving thought) all the trade will wholly come
to me, <hi>and I ſhall be repleniſhed</hi> and encreaſed. No
more. Yet, becauſe it fell out to be uttered againſt the
Church, for this, and for no other ſinne (there men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned)
muſt <hi>Tyre</hi> be deſtroyed, as ſhe was by <hi>Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezzar,</hi>
though to fulfill the Propheſie, he <hi>ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved</hi>
twelve yeares in the ſiege thereof. And ſee how
God proportioned her puniſhment to her ſinne;
Wouldſt thou have more cuſtomers? Thou ſhalt
have enow; <hi>Behold, I will cauſe many Nations to come
up;</hi> What, for traffique? No, <hi>to come up againſt thee,
as the ſea cauſeth his waves to come up:</hi> the Babylonian
Souldiers ſhall be thy Merchants that ſhall take off
thy goods off thy hands. And becauſe that <hi>Tyre,</hi>
was a moſt glorious people, he therefore ſpends
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:159563:12"/>
two or three Chapters upon the deſcription of her
ruine.</p>
            <p>In the 26.<note place="margin">6. AEgypt.</note> Chapter he comes to <hi>Egypt. Egypt</hi> had
been broken once afore (as you heard) by the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
of Iſrael, and reproved for <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſake. They
were a falſe-hearted Nation, that even <hi>Rabſhekah</hi> could
afore-hand propheſie ſo of them, in <hi>Eſay 36. 6. Lo,</hi>
ſaith he, <hi>thou truſteſt on the ſtaffe of this broken reede,
whereon if a man will leane, it will goe into his hand and
pierce it; ſo is Pharaoh King of Egypt to all that truſt in him.</hi>
Twas the <hi>Genius</hi> of that Nation to all that dealt with
them. And as <hi>Rabſhekah</hi> had foretold of them, ſo it fell
out: and therefore the Prophet <hi>Ezech.</hi> utters their ſin
againſt the Church in <hi>Rabſhekahs</hi> language, <hi>Chap.</hi> 29. 7.
<hi>Becauſe they have been a ſtaffe of reed to the houſe of Iſrael.</hi>
It is a moſt elegant compariſon; the ſimilitude it looks
many wayes: 1. A <hi>Reed</hi> was a Hieroglyphick of that
Country. <hi>Sanctius</hi> upon thoſe words, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 68. 30.
<hi>Rebuke the company of the Spearmen,</hi> (ſo we tranſlate it)
but look in the margent of your Bibles, and likewiſe
the Originall will beare it, it is, <hi>Rebuke the beaſt of the
Reeds,</hi> and he interpreteth this to be meant of <hi>Egypt,</hi>
the Chaldee Paraphraſe alſo interpreting it of that
Nation, it being a Country of <hi>Reeds.</hi> On the bank
of <hi>Nylus,</hi> and ſo throughout the whole Countrey,
(through the overflowing of that River) there were,
and are ſuch Reeds &amp; Canes growing,<note place="margin">Lib. 16. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 36.</note> as no where in
the world againe beſides, (ſo <hi>Pliny</hi> ſaith) ſerving for
<hi>Pens, Speares, Arrowes</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Hence <hi>Arun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do</hi> for <hi>Sagitta</hi> with the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines, and the ſame word for a <hi>Reed</hi> and a <hi>Spear</hi> (as here) in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</note> (as <hi>Pliny</hi> there) ſo for
<hi>Staves, Arkes, Exodus</hi> 2. 3. And <hi>Egypt</hi> is called a
BEAST <hi>of reeds,</hi> alluding further (as I take it) to the
Crocodile, the proper beaſt of that Countrey, which
is an <hi>Amphibion,</hi> living both in land and water; and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:159563:12"/>
ſo uſually lies amongſt the reeds by the river ſide,<note place="margin">As the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant alſo is ſaid to doe, <hi>Job</hi> 40. 21.</note> and
there ſhrowds her ſelf againſt the heat. And ſuitably
we finde that <hi>Auguſtus</hi> having conquered <hi>Anthony</hi>
and <hi>Cleopatra</hi> the Queene of <hi>Egypt,</hi> cauſed by way of
triumph to be ſtamped on his Coyne a <hi>Crocodile</hi> and
a <hi>Reed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">And in <hi>Adrians</hi> coynes of gold alſo.</note> as that which was put for the <hi>Hieroglyphick</hi> of
that Country, as the manner of the Romans was.
And the holy Ghoſt here in <hi>Ezechiel</hi> long before
ſeemes to have given the ſame Coat of Armes for
that Country and Kingdome, (perhaps according to
the common uſe) uſing both theſe apart of <hi>Egypt</hi>
alſo. For firſt, in the third verſe of this <hi>Chap.</hi> 29. he
calleth <hi>Pharaoh</hi> King of <hi>Egypt, The Dragon of the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers,</hi>
(which I beleeve hath reference to the <hi>Croco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dile,</hi>
in thoſe Rivers, which is a kind of Serpent, and
beaſt alſo) and in the 7. verſe after, which we are
now upon, to <hi>a ſtaffe of reed.</hi> Whereas in that 68. Pſal.
you ſee both are put together, <hi>The beaſt of reeds:</hi> Here
in this 29. of <hi>Ezechiel,</hi> the Prophet having in his eye
the common Hieroglyphick of the Countrey, turnes
the ſimilitude to their being <hi>a ſtaffe of reed;</hi> that ſuiting
his preſent ſcope, which was to expreſſe their failing
that confidence the people of God repoſed in them,
and ſo becomming the fatall occaſion of their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie.
BECAUSE (ſaith he, verſe 6.) <hi>thou haſt beene a
ſtaffe of reed to the houſe of Iſrael, when they took hold of
thee thou didſt breake:</hi> They (as <hi>Cornelius à Lapide</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
the place) had provoked the Jews to rebel againſt
<hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> promiſing to aſſiſt them; But though
thou wert <hi>Baculus in promiſsione, a ſtaffe</hi> in <hi>promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi>
yet but <hi>Arundinens in executione,</hi> a ſtaffe of <hi>reed,</hi>
vaine and helpleſſe in the <hi>performance,</hi> (as he ſpeaks.)
The Prophet goes on. Yea thou didſt not onely
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:159563:13"/>
break, but run up, and <hi>rend all the ſhoulder, and madeſt
their loynes to be at a ſtand;</hi> didſt not onely hinder, but
hurt and weaken them. The Lord comes upon them
with his former THEREFORE, ver. 8. <hi>ſaith the Lord,
I will bring a ſword upon thee, and will cut off man and
beaſt.</hi> And ſo he goes on in three or foure Chapters to
ſet forth their puniſhment, and that relating as the
former had done, to this their unfaithfull dealing
with Gods people, as that ſinne that was the cauſe
thereof, which is the point in hand.</p>
            <p>When the Prophet had thus diſpatched <hi>Egypt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">7. A ſpeciall threatning a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt mount <hi>Seir</hi> and <hi>Edom.</hi>
               </note> and
threatned the like to <hi>Aſſyria</hi> and <hi>Babylon,</hi> (of which e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough
was touched before) he fals afreſh upon mount
<hi>Seir</hi> and <hi>Edom,</hi> and contents not himſelfe to have put
them into the common catalogue (which we have
gone over) with the reſt of the Nations in the 25.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſau,</hi> of whom both came, was called <hi>Edom</hi> for his <hi>Redneſſe, Gen.</hi> 25. 30. &amp; <hi>Seir</hi> from his <hi>hayrie hands. Eſau</hi> dwelt in <hi>Seir, Gen.</hi> 33. 14, 16. and was given as a poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion to his ſeed by God, <hi>Deut.</hi> 2. 5. and <hi>Eſau</hi> was the father of <hi>Edom, Gen. 36. ult.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Chap.</hi> but he returns again to a peculiar, ſpecial recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
with them in the 35. Chapter, (the reaſon of it
we ſhall ſee by and by, becauſe they were their <hi>bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren)
Becauſe</hi> (ſaith he there, ver. 5.) <hi>thou haſt had a
perpetuall hatred, and haſt ſhed the blood of the children of
Iſrael by the force of the ſword in the time of their calamity,
in the time that their iniquity</hi> HAD AN END, that is, when
they had already ſuffered ſo much for their ſins, that it
might have been thought God had puniſhed them e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough,
yet then doe they begin their miſery afreſh:
<hi>Therefore as I live, ſaith the Lord, I will prepare thee unto
blood, and blood ſhall purſue thee, &amp;c.</hi> And <hi>ver.</hi> 10. he
addes another reaſon, <hi>Becauſe thou haſt ſaid, Theſe two
nations, and theſe two countries ſhall be mine,</hi> (namely,
their owne, and that of Iſrael adjoyning) <hi>and we will
poſſeſſe it:</hi> when <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> had laid it waſte, they
promiſed to themſelves the poſſeſſion of it, <hi>where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:159563:13"/>
THE LORD WAS THERE, (as the Prophet
addes) They thought they might as eaſily conquer,
and enter upon the poſſeſſion of it, as any of the other
Nations, whereas the Lords preſence was there,
to keep poſſeſſion for himſelfe and his people that
belonged unto it: This was their ſinne, then follows
their puniſhment. <hi>Therefore as I live, ſaith the Lord, I
will even doe according to thine anger, and according to
thine envie, which thou haſt uſed out of thy hatred againſt
them,</hi> I will proportion my puniſhment accordingly.
And he doth not content himſelfe onely with this
bringing of them in again here, but beſides he ſpends
a whole Propheſie upon them, the Propheſie of <hi>Oba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diah,</hi>
whoſe meſſage is taken up with nothing but
threatnings againſt <hi>Edom,</hi> and reſolving all into the
ſame quarrel, <hi>For thy violence againſt thy</hi> BROTHER <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Deut. 2. 4, 5. <hi>God ſaid to the Jewes,</hi> You are to paſſe through the coaſt of your <hi>BRETHREN</hi> the children of Eſau. Meddle not with them, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Edom</hi> and <hi>Seir</hi> (as was ſaid) comming of <hi>Eſau</hi>
were <hi>brethren</hi> to the Iſraelites, and God takes it infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely
more unkindly at their hands, then at the
hands of the other Nations, THEREFORE <hi>ſhame
ſhall cover thee, and thou ſhalt be cut off for ever. In
the day that thou ſtoodſt on the other ſide,</hi> that is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>havedſt
thy ſelfe as a neuter that ſtood aloofe: <hi>in the
day that ſtrangers carryed away captive his forces, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigners
entred into his gates, and caſt lots upon Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,
thou waſt as</hi> ONE OF THEM, didſt as much
miſchief as the Babylonians.<note place="margin">The Pſalmiſt alſo hath it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 137. 7.</note> 
               <hi>Thou ſhouldſt not have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred
into the gate of my people in the day of their calamity,
yea thou ſhouldſt not have looked on their affliction,</hi> (that is,
as idle Spectators, much leſſe rejoycers in it) <hi>nor have
laid hands on their ſubſtance,</hi> not have ſpoiled them of
their goods, <hi>in the day of their calamity &amp;c.</hi> Therefore is
their puniſhment to a perpetuall ruine, more heavy
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:159563:14"/>
then any of the reſt. Thus now you have alſo ſeene
an end of all theſe Kingdomes that were neighbours
about <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and how they were all <hi>reproved,</hi> yea
<hi>deſtroyed,</hi> upon this quarrell of <hi>touching,</hi> and medling
with his <hi>anointed,</hi> as the Text hath it.</p>
            <p>Now let us goe on to the other Monarchies,<note place="margin">V. The <hi>Perſian</hi> Monarchy an inſtance of Gods bleſſing for his peoples ſakes.</note> the
<hi>Perſian</hi> and the <hi>Grecian:</hi> you ſhall ſee ſtill that the ſtory
of them alſo makes good this great point in hand.
The <hi>Perſian</hi> and the <hi>Grecian</hi> both had to doe with the
Church: But the firſt of theſe, the <hi>Perſian,</hi> ſeems ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
an inſtance on the other hand, <hi>viz.</hi> of the <hi>wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare,</hi>
and of <hi>the raiſing up of a Nation and of a State</hi> for
the people of God: (For God hath given ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances
of bleſſing as well as he hath given of ruine.)
The very raiſing up of <hi>Cyrus,</hi> and of that Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie
in him, it was for his peoples ſake. The Scripture
is expreſſe for this, reade <hi>Eſay 44. 28. Thus ſaith God
of Cyrus, He is my ſhepherd, and ſhall performe all my plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,
even ſaying to Ieruſalem, Thou ſhalt be built, and to
the Temple, Thy foundation ſhall be laid.</hi> And goe on to
<hi>Chap. 45. ver. 1. Thus ſaith the Lord to his anointed, to
Cyrus, whoſe right hand I have holden, to ſubdue Nations
before him, &amp;c.</hi> He calls <hi>Cyrus His</hi> ANOYNTED: He
calls <hi>Tyre An anointed covering Cherub</hi> alſo, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 28.
and no other Heathen Princes elſe in all the Booke
of God: Firſt, <hi>Tyre an anointed Cherub,</hi> becauſe he
was propitious to the Jewes, even as the <hi>Cherub</hi> co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering
the <hi>Arke:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Occolampad. in loc.</note> Then <hi>Cyrus</hi> was <hi>Anointed,</hi> becauſe
as <hi>Sanctius</hi> well ſaith, <hi>Non minus ſtudioſe res curabat
Iudaicas quam ſi Iudaeorum eſſet, &amp; non Perſaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Imperator.</hi>
He took as much care for the people of God, and the
building of the Temple, as if he had been King of
<hi>Iury</hi> himſelfe. And God calleth him likewiſe his
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:159563:14"/>
SHEPHERD, even as he had done <hi>David,</hi> that was to
look to his ſheep. In the place I quoted before, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
the Aſſyrian and Babylonian Kings, <hi>Ier.</hi> 50.
you heard how he called them LIONS, becauſe they
<hi>ſcattered his ſheep,</hi> ſo the expreſſion is there, but here he
calls <hi>Cyrus</hi> HIS SHEPHERD, <hi>that ſhall performe all his
pleaſure:</hi> and for that end raiſed him to all this great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe:
for, for whoſe ſake was it, he had the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
given him? Reade the fourth verſe, <hi>For</hi> JACOB
<hi>my</hi> SERVANTS SAKE, <hi>and Iſrael mine elect, I have e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
called thee by thy name, I have ſurnamed thee, though
thou haſt not knowne me:</hi> not for thy ſake, but for my
peoples only. And although for a while ſome of them
Kings made Edicts to interrupt the building of the
Temple, yet the generality of thoſe Kings went on
in that courſe of favour which <hi>Cyrus</hi> had begun, and
were more favourable to the Jewes then all of the
other Monarchies. <hi>Darius Hiſtaſpis</hi> mentioned <hi>Ezra</hi>
4. <hi>ver.</hi> 24. permitted the Jewes to goe on in buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
it, as their poverty would ſuffer them; and after
another interruption, <hi>Darius Nothus,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Thus <hi>Calviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> and Maſter <hi>Mede</hi> in his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niels Weeks,</hi> pag. 5, 6, 7. which doth fall in the beſt to accord all the yeares of <hi>Dani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els</hi> Weeks. But if (as moſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Chrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logers) it had beene <hi>Darius Hiſtaſpis</hi> that made that Decree in <hi>Ezra</hi> 6. for the finiſhing the Temple, then it affords a greater Obſervation to my purpoſe in hand, namely, That God did take away <hi>Cambyſes, Cyrus</hi> his ſonne, (whom they would have to be that <hi>Artaxerxes, Ezra</hi> 4. that hindred by force of Arms the building the Temple both in his Fathers dayes (whilſt he was <hi>Prince of Perſia,</hi> as <hi>Dan.</hi> 10. 13. he is called, or <hi>Prorex</hi> in his fathers abſence) and in his owne) and that without iſſue, and ſo <hi>Cyrus</hi> iſſue male ended, being puniſht for recalling the favour granted. But <hi>Darius Hiſtaſpis</hi> being choſen by the Princes, God eſtabliſhed the Kingdom in him and his ſeed, for his reviving <hi>Cyrus</hi> his Edict. And however, almoſt all agree in this, that this <hi>Darius</hi> he hindred it not, but gave liberty for his time, and is that <hi>Darius</hi> mentioned <hi>Ezra</hi> 4 24. See <hi>Mede, Daniels Weeks.</hi> pag. 7. in his marginall note, whom there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God bleſſed accordingly, and yet regarded <hi>Cyrus</hi> alſo in this, that by his daughter <hi>Atoſſa</hi> wife to this <hi>Darius,</hi> his race continued.</note> 
               <hi>Ezra</hi> 6. did put
<hi>Cyrus</hi> his Decree in force againe, and allowes the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence
of the finiſhing it out of his owne revenues, and
inſerts this in his revived Decree, that the Jewes
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:159563:15"/>
might <hi>pray for the life of the King and of his children,
ver.</hi> 10. They alſo had of the ſeed of the Jews great
men at Court with them, as <hi>Daniel, Mordecat, Ezra,</hi> and
<hi>Nehemiah,</hi> the two latter of whom were ſent by <hi>Arta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xerxes</hi>
to build the City of Jeruſalem; yea, &amp; another
of their Kings admitted one of that Nation (through
the providence of God) to the royall bed: <hi>Ahaſueroſh</hi>
marryed <hi>Heſter,</hi> of the ſeed of the Jews, under whom,
and under other of theſe Kings they had the greateſt
proſperity. Now as this favour to the Jews was the
cauſe of the erecting that Monarchie at firſt, ſo ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
of the continuance of it ſo long: Hiſtorians won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
that it ſhould ſtand ſo long, it being ſo looſe and
diſſolute a Court and State<note n="*" place="margin">Therefore <hi>Daniel</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares him to a ſlow unweildy <hi>Ram,</hi> as it were heavy with, wool and fleſh, <hi>Chap.</hi> 8 7.</note> and having ſo many great
ſhocks. I can attribute it to nothing but this, the emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent
favour they ſhewed to the Jewes, the people of
God. And I ſhall but caſt in this Obſervation more
about it. When was it that it came to be ruined and
deſtroyed? but in the time of the latter <hi>Darius,</hi> then
when <hi>Cyrus</hi> (who had been <hi>Gods Shepherd</hi>) his ſeed
was wholly extinct?<note n="*" place="margin">Diodo. imitio. lib. 7.</note> For though his ſeed by the Male
iſſue continued not to a Grandchild, yet in the ſeed of
<hi>Atoſſa, Cyrus</hi> daughter, wife to <hi>Darius Hiſtaſpis,</hi> the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
was continued in his race. And to make the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence
the more remarkable, wheras <hi>Darius</hi> had ſons
before by another wife, yet the intreſt of <hi>Atoſſa</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſayes <hi>Herodotus</hi> of <hi>Atoſſa,</hi> giving it as the reaſon of this ſucceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> for <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi>
ſake, carryed the ſucceſſion to <hi>Xerxes</hi> her ſon, <hi>Cyrus</hi>
Grandchild. But <hi>that</hi> laſt <hi>Darius,</hi> in &amp; with whom that
Empire was deſtroyed by <hi>Alexander,</hi> was of another
race<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great in his Letters to <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius,</hi> and his ſpeech to his ſoldiers againſt <hi>Darius,</hi> affirms it. <hi>Arrianus Cu<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tius, lib.</hi> 6. us alſo <hi>Juſtin.</hi>
               </note>. Such regard had God to <hi>Cyrus</hi> his Shepherd,
and his ſeed, that favoured the Jewes. But then it
was, and not afore, that God threw down that Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy,
whether for any thing done againſt the people
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:159563:15"/>
of God or no, the Scripture is ſilent.</p>
            <p>Let us come to the <hi>Grecian</hi> Monarchy,<note place="margin">VI. The <hi>Greci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> Monarchy.</note> for that was
the third; ſome of the ſtory of which, you have men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned
in <hi>Zech.</hi> 9. which is an apparent Propheſie of
the expedition of <hi>Alexander:</hi>
               <note place="margin">D. <hi>Jackſon</hi> 8. Book of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaries on the Creed, ſect. 3 6. 17.</note> and as a late learned
Writer rightly ſaith, you may better know the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
of the firſt part of that Chapter out of <hi>Quintus
Curtius</hi> and <hi>Joſephus,</hi> then out of moſt Commenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors.
You reade there of a Propheſie of <hi>Tyre</hi> that it
muſt be taken againe, ſo <hi>verſ.</hi> 3. Now <hi>Zechariah</hi> writ
after the Babyloniſh Captivity, therefore it is not
that former taking of <hi>Tyre</hi> by <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> but
that latter by <hi>Alexander.</hi> And what he ſayes in the
5. <hi>ver.</hi> of <hi>Gaza,</hi> and thoſe other Cities in <hi>Philiſtia,
Askelon ſhall not be inhabited,</hi> and the <hi>cutting off the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour
of Gaza, Quintus Curtius</hi> exactly relates the
performance of it, and his cruelty therein; and it is
uſually noted as the firſt and greateſt act of <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi>
degenerating to barbarous inhumanity: Now
all <hi>that</hi> his rage againſt all thoſe Cities that were
neighbours to the Jewes, was ordered by God, and
foretold by the Prophet, but onely to ſet forth the
wonderfull care and protection of God towards his
people, recorded <hi>ver.</hi> 8. that although <hi>Alexander</hi> was
as much incenſed againſt the Jews, (for their anſwer
ſent him of their reſolution to cleave to <hi>Darius,</hi> to
whom they had ſworne) yet as that 8. verſe fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told,
I WILL ENCAMP ABOUT MY HOUSE, ſayes
God, <hi>becauſe of</hi> THE ARMY, <hi>becauſe of him that paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth
by, and becauſe of him that returneth.</hi> When <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi>
went by, and when afterwards many other Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
went to and fro, God ſtill encamped about his
houſe. And though <hi>Alexander</hi> plundered or deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:159563:16"/>
all the Cities round about, yet ſtill Jeruſalem and
the Temple were preſerved. Yea <hi>Alexanders</hi> heart
was ſo changed, (as <hi>Eſaus</hi>) that he went in peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly.
And the High Prieſt ſhewing him the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie
of <hi>Daniel,</hi> how the King of <hi>Grecia,</hi> that is,
himſelfe, ſhould overcome the King of <hi>Perſia:</hi> he
was thereby encouraged to the conqueſt of the
King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> and not onely ſpared them, but
gave many immunities to the Jewes: and in that
his expedition againſt <hi>Darius,</hi> proſpered accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly.</p>
            <p>Now that Monarchie thus raiſed by him, was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided
into <hi>foure parts, Dan.</hi> 8. 22. all which are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted
to make up that <hi>Grecian</hi> Monarchie: And <hi>in
the latter end of their Kingdome,</hi> ſayes the 23. verſe, <hi>when
the tranſgreſsions are come to the full,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joſeph. Antiq. Jud li. 11.</note> that is, when God
meant to begin to break it, and to put a period to
it, and to reckon with them for their other ſins. This
his wonted deſigne ſets his providence awork, that
they ſhould fall foule upon his people, and ſo be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken,
as the former had been; and eminently among
and above the reſt, you have a <hi>little horne</hi> ariſing,
<hi>Antiochus,</hi> the ſucceſſour of one of them; (the ſtory is
cleare in <hi>Dan.</hi> 8. who <hi>magnified himſelfe againſt the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
of God,</hi> the <hi>daily ſacrifice,</hi> againſt <hi>the truth, &amp;c. ver.</hi>
11, 12. and in this God laid the foundation not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
of his ruine, but of the reſt of the <hi>Grecian</hi> Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie.
This I might ſhew out of <hi>Daniel, ver. 25. He
ſhall be broken without hand,</hi> &amp;c. but I will rather do
it out of the 9. of <hi>Zachary,</hi> (having already begun with
<hi>that,</hi> and ſhewed out of it the riſe and proceedings of
that Monarchie in the <hi>firſt horne</hi> thereof, <hi>Alexander</hi>)
let us ſee what it ſayes of the ruine of it, in that which
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:159563:16"/>
followes, <hi>ver. 13. When I have bent Judah for me,
and filled the bow with Ephraim,</hi> (it is an elegant ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude)
<hi>and raiſed up thy ſonnes,</hi> O ZION, <hi>againſt thy
ſonnes</hi> O GREECE, <hi>and made thee as the ſword of a
mighty man: And the Lord ſhall be ſeene over them,
and his arrow ſhall goe forth as the lightning, &amp;c.</hi> Here
the Grecian Monarchie in the laſt remainders of it
(the Kings of <hi>Egypt</hi> and <hi>Syria,</hi> the <hi>Longidae</hi> and <hi>Seleu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidae</hi>
who both oppreſſed the Jewes, being there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
called GREECE,<note place="margin">They are called <hi>Greece,</hi> as the King of <hi>Perſia</hi> is called <hi>King of Aſhur, Ezr.</hi> 6. 22. and as <hi>Cyrus, Ez.</hi> 5. 13. and <hi>Artaxerxes Neh.</hi> 10. 6. are called <hi>Kings of Babel,</hi> becauſe ſucceſſours to theſe Kings.</note> becauſe they were the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors
of it) is ruined: and by whom? even by the
people of the Jewes, or for their ſakes. God rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
up <hi>the ſonnes of Sion</hi> againſt theſe <hi>ſonnes of Greece,
God made Judah his bow, and Ephraim his arrowes:</hi>
(and when God himſelfe will be the Archer, weake
arrowes and inſtruments will doe wonders) And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides,
that for their ſakes God uſed miraculous and
wonderfull wayes to ruine theſe enemies, <hi>The Lord
ſhall be ſeene over them, &amp;c. ver.</hi> 14. God uſed the
Jewes themſelves, the <hi>Maccabees,</hi> to vindicate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
againſt theſe reliques of the Grecian Empire,
as the ſtory in the book of the <hi>Maccabees</hi> ſhewes plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
(as Interpreters upon the Text have obſerved) and
particularly how <hi>Antiochus</hi> came to his end: And
afterwards the ruine of the whole by the <hi>Romans,</hi> it
was for the Jews ſake, and their quarrell, and at their
prayer; it was by <hi>Ephraim</hi> being his <hi>arrow,</hi> and <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah</hi>
his <hi>bow,</hi> and <hi>God</hi> himſelfe appearing from heaven
againſt them. So then here the GRECIAN MONAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHY
is likewiſe broken upon the Jewes. And thus
we have done with the Old Teſtamet.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:159563:17"/>
Now let us come to the <hi>New Teſtament.</hi>
               <note place="margin">NEW TE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STAMENT. The Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplified in the <hi>Jews</hi> ſtate and <hi>Romane Empire.</hi>
               </note> Our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt
who was the eminent <hi>anointed one,</hi> he comes obſcure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
and as it were ſtealing into the world, who was to
be King of all the world, in the dayes of him, who
laid the firſt ſure foundation, and ſettlement of the
<hi>Romane Empire,</hi> namely, <hi>Auguſtus;</hi> and he comes <hi>to
his owne,</hi> to the people of the Jewes, over whom the
<hi>Romanes</hi> having the power, and a Preſident amongſt
them, our Saviour came to have to doe at once with
both theſe States.</p>
            <p>And firſt for the Jewes.<note place="margin">1. The Jewiſh.</note> Becauſe that which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fell
that State for their dealing with Chriſt and his
Diſciples, is the leading caſe of the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
as what was done to theſe Kings and Nations
here in the Text, and <hi>in</hi> the ſtory of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> for their
carriage towards <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> was the
leading caſe of the Old: I will therefore begin there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with,
and ſpend a little time in the opening of it, ſo
farre as it concernes the point in hand.</p>
            <p>And now you ſhall ſee that <hi>Nation</hi> &amp; <hi>State,</hi> of which
hitherto you have heard, that it had beene for the
<hi>riſing</hi> or <hi>falling</hi> of all the Monarchies, and alſo leſſer
Kingdomes round about it; it ſelfe to be the firſt of
all other that was broken and ruined under the <hi>New
Teſtament,</hi> as an example to all the reſt that follow:
and broken not upon another whole Nation like
it ſelf, but upon <hi>a few,</hi> &amp; <hi>a very few anointed ones</hi> in that
Nation, namely, Our <hi>Lord</hi> and his <hi>Diſciples.</hi> God
altering now the way of his diſpenſation under the
<hi>New Teſtament,</hi> uſing but a few Saints in Nations,
(which is the more glorious) to effect the ſame de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:159563:17"/>
he did before by that whole Nation of the
Jewes under the Old.<note place="margin">Revel. 5. 9.</note> 
               <hi>He hath redeemed us</hi> (ſay
they) <hi>out of all Nations,</hi> (who are to him <hi>a royall
Nation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2. 9 com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with Chap. 1. 1.</note> typified out by that whole Nation of the
Jewes) whom now he maketh to be to all Kingdoms
(where they are found) either <hi>a ſtone of ſtumbling,</hi>
whereby they ſhall be broken, or a ſure Baſis and
foundation of their wel-fare, according to their uſage
of them.</p>
            <p>How the Jews uſed Chriſt and his Diſciples, we
all know. The intereſt of that Nation, wherein ſtood
it? Not ſo much to have entertained Chriſt for their
Temporall King, he avoided that; but to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived
him for their <hi>Meſsiah,</hi> and <hi>anointed</hi> Saviour: and
that this was the intereſt of the Nation and its well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare,
is cleere by that ſpeech of Chriſt, <hi>Luke</hi> 19. 42.
<hi>Oh that thou hadſt knowne in this thy day the things that
belong unto thy peace!</hi> He therein intending as well the
<hi>Temporall peace</hi> of that <hi>Nation,</hi> as the <hi>eternall peace</hi> of
their <hi>ſoules.</hi> As <hi>Tyre</hi> had <hi>ſtood to that day if they had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented,</hi>
(as <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſpeaks) ſo had <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> alſo <hi>if they
had knowne</hi> and kept to this their INTEREST. But they
were ſo farre from doing this, that they clean diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
from it, and took up other worldly and politique
<hi>intereſts</hi> of their owne, to ſave themſelves by, which
were their ruine. Yea (which I beſeech you mark and
obſerve) the Lord did order it ſo in his providence,
that even REASON OF STATE, and a <hi>word</hi> lye croſſe
INTEREST, to this ſhould be the chiefe motive to
them of <hi>crucifying Chriſt,</hi> and ſo of the finall deſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
on of that Nation. For which, conſult firſt the 11. of
<hi>John, ver,</hi> 49, 50. ſay they (generally) <hi>If we let him
thus alone, all men will beleeve on him, and the</hi> ROMANS
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:159563:18"/>
               <hi>will come and take away both our place and Nation.</hi> And
what ſaith the great High-Prieſt further upon it?
<hi>Ye know nothing at all, nor conſider that it is expedient
for</hi> US, <hi>that one man ſhould dye for the people, and that
the whole Nation periſh not.</hi> And although this is there
ſaid, to be ſpoken as a Propheſie, (God guiding his
mouth therein) yet withall, if you look into the 18.
of <hi>John, ver.</hi> 14. it is charged upon him to have been
a wicked <hi>councell</hi> given, (take it as it was intended by
him) for there he is branded, <hi>This is</hi> THAT CAIAPHAS
<hi>that gave</hi> COUNSELL <hi>to the Jews, that it was expedient
that one man ſhould die for the people.</hi> How it might
be both theſe, as directed by God, and intended by
him, would be too long to ſhew. But take it as it thus
came from him, and he takes on him as High-Prieſt
to ſpeake as a deepe Oracle of State, and to utter a
<hi>State-Maxime,</hi> with ſleighting of his fellowes, <hi>You
know nothing,</hi> and his <hi>Maxime</hi> followes, <hi>Better</hi> that <hi>one
man,</hi> who is not conſiderable, be <hi>taken away, then a
Nation periſh.</hi> And yet he therein had an eye to the
Prieſts intereſt, that is, of himſelfe and his fellows,
to keep up their honour; as well as to the preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of the Nation, though he colours it over with that
of the whole Nation. For in <hi>John</hi> 11. 50. the words
are, <hi>It is expedient</hi> FOR Us, (namely, Prieſts) <hi>that one
man ſhould dye for the people.</hi> They were jealous of <hi>Chriſt</hi>
getting the people from them. You ſhal likewiſe find,
that when the matter was brought to <hi>Pilate,</hi> it was
<hi>State intereſt</hi> alſo cauſed <hi>Pilate</hi> to come off to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demne
him, <hi>The Jewes cryed out, If thou let this man goe, thou
art not Caeſars friend: Whoſoever maketh himſelf a King,
ſpeaketh againſt Caeſar:</hi> And the Text addes, <hi>When Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late</hi>
THEREFORE <hi>heard that ſaying, He ſate downe and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:159563:18"/>
condemned him,</hi> John 19. 12, 13. When I read and
conſidered this ſtory, it made me underſtand that in
1 <hi>Cor. 2. 6. We ſpeak not the</hi> WISDOME OF THIS
WORLD, <hi>nor of the Princes of this world, that comes to
nought; but we ſpeak the wiſdome of God in a myſterie,</hi>
which NONE OF THE PRINCES OF THIS
WORLD KNEW, <hi>for had they knowne it, they would</hi>
NOT HAVE CRUCIFYED THE LORD OF GLORY.
He ſpeakes of theſe very <hi>Princes</hi> the <hi>Rulers of the
Jews,</hi> and of <hi>Pilate;</hi> and the holy Ghost you ſee ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
the very ſame Obſervation upon it, that I have
now done to you. They thought themſelves wiſe,
and they went upon axioms of State in doing of it,
but had they knowne their intereſt, they would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
have crucified the Lord of glory. And the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle,
you ſee, gives this as the greateſt and moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent
inſtance of the folly, of State-policie which often
Princes take up, againſt <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and the <hi>Wiſdome of the
Goſpel,</hi> the true Wiſdome. And it is farther obſervable
to this purpoſe, what likewiſe the Apoſtle ſaith in the
following <hi>Chap.</hi> 3. 17. applying the ſame in ſubſtance
which hee here had obſerved upon their crucify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
Chriſt, unto the defiling or deſtroying the
Church of God, the Saints, which is the point in
hsnd) whom Chriſt hath left behinde him, out
of the like Carnall wiſdome and worldly policie,
IF ANY MAN DEFILE OR DESTROY THE
TEMPLE OF GOD, HIM SHALL GOD DESTROY:
<hi>for the Temple of God is holy,</hi> WHICH TEMPLE ARE
YE. Let no man deceive himſelfe; If any man among you
SEEMETH TO BE WISE IN THIS WORLD,
let him become a foole that he may be wiſe; for the wiſdome
of this world is fooliſhneſſe with God; for it is written,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:159563:19"/>
HE TAKETH THE WISE IN THEIR OWNE
CRAFTYNES. As God caught thoſe <hi>Jewiſh Princes</hi>
and <hi>Prieſts</hi> in their owne <hi>craftineſſe</hi> againſt Chriſt, ſo
will he for ever doe thoſe,<note place="margin">It is the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of Doctor <hi>Jack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it openeth a Scripture, I will give in his owne words: <q>Out of this undoubted <hi>prenotion,</hi> that this was the very time wherein the Lord had promiſed to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver this peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from the hands of their enemies, they became ſo prone (as the event proves they were) to take Arms and rebell againſt the Romans, partly about the time of our Saviours birth, <hi>but eſpecially after his Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</hi>
                  </q> There was no man <hi>of great might or potency</hi> among them, which did not take upon him, to promiſe this peoples deliverance from the <hi>Romane</hi> yoke; and the multitude were as prone to beleeve every one that would take upon him the name and title of a <hi>Saviour,</hi> or Deliverer. The fore-fight of this proneneſſe in great ones to promiſe ſalvation to this people, and the peoples proneneſſe to beleeve them, did occaſion our Saviour to give thoſe admonitions to his Diſciples, <hi>Beware of falſe Chriſts, Matth. 24. ver. 4. Mark 13. ver. 6. Luke 21. ver.</hi> 6. which would ariſe in <hi>Jury</hi> before the deſtruction of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> with ſuch faire enticing promiſes and pretences of deliverance, <hi>that if it had been poſſible, the very Elect ſhould have been deceived by them.</hi> In a Sermon upon <hi>Luke</hi> 21. 25.</note> that offer violence to his
Saints, eſpecially when out of ſtate and worldly
intereſts. That theſe Jews were taken in their own
craftineſſe, if it needed, might largely be ſhewne;
the thing they feared and avoided was brought up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
them; the Romans came and took away their
place and Nation to this day: yea and it was great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
occaſioned by the ſame motive which in policy
they embraced, whereby to avoid it. For as
the riſing of many <hi>falſe Chriſts</hi> was the curſe of that
Nation for refuſing the <hi>True,</hi> and is made the ſigne of
their deſtruction by our Saviour, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24. ſo it was the
Jews proneneſſe to beleeve that their <hi>Meſsiah</hi> ſhould
come about that time, and deliver them from the
Romane yoke, that the more encouraged them in
their Rebellion and revolt from the Romans, which
occaſioned their utter deſtruction by them. And
ſo <hi>Tacitus,</hi> yea and <hi>Joſephus</hi> alſo did thereupon,
interpret that Jewiſh Propheſie <hi>of the King of the
world to come out of Jury,</hi> of <hi>veſpaſian</hi> himſelfe, that
was the deſtroyer of them, (he comming a Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor
out of <hi>Jury,</hi> who was Lord of the world) God
thus retorting out of the mouthes of theſe two wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes,
a <hi>Heathen</hi> and a <hi>Jew,</hi> their former ſinne in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:159563:19"/>
their <hi>naturall Lord,</hi> the <hi>true King</hi> (indeed) <hi>of
all the world,</hi> his ſonne: Thus returning it (I ſay) with
the higheſt <hi>Reproofe</hi> upon theſe Jewes, by this, that
<hi>that</hi> Emperour of <hi>Rome</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Veſpaſian.</note> (their enemy and deſtroyer,
together with his ſonne<note n="*" place="margin">Titus.</note>) ſhould obtaine and carry
away the repute of that Propheſie (they relyed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
too late) and this becauſe they came out of <hi>Judea,</hi>
from the executing that vengeance the Jews had
by this brought upon their owne heads.<note place="margin">His blood be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us and our children, <hi>ſaid they, who had formerly ſaid of the greateſt Kingdomes in their ruines,</hi> My blood upon Caldea ſhall Jeruſalem ſay, <hi>Jer.</hi> 51. 35.</note> This ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
beene manifeſtly the deſtruction of that
Nation, and being likewiſe the pattern of the New
Teſtament. Give me leave to give you this further
obſervation by the way about it: That God diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed
it in his providence ſo, that all States and
ſorts of men among them ſhould have their hands in
it, becauſe Gods purpoſe is not to deſtroy any Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
for his peoples ſake, till all ſorts therein concur in
their ill uſing of them. The ſecond Pſalme Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecying
of the crucifying of Chriſt, ſayes, that <hi>the
Heathen, the people, the Kings of the earth, the Rulers,
tooke counſell againſt the Lords Anointed,</hi> which the
Apoſtles in their Prayer (of which by and by) <hi>Acts</hi>
4. 27. interpret, <hi>That Herod, Pontius Pilate, with the
Gentiles, and the people of Iſrael, were gathered together
againſt his child Jeſus:</hi> both the <hi>Eccleſiaſticall</hi> and the
<hi>Civill</hi> ſtate among the <hi>Jewes,</hi> concurred in it. The <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedrim</hi>
firſt, and Elders of the people; and they with
much adoe <hi>perſwade the people;</hi>
               <note place="margin">The chiefe Prieſts and El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders perſwaded the multitude, <hi>Mat.</hi> 27. 20.</note> and when that was with
difficulty done, it was long ere <hi>Pilate</hi> did conſent; he
kept off, and <hi>waſht his hands,</hi> though the people, Prieſts
and all ſought to him; but in the end yeelded. And
what was the reaſon that <hi>Pilate</hi> came in at length al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo?
Becauſe God would have the Romane Empire,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:159563:20"/>
(which he meant to break upon Chriſt and his Saints
as the former) to be wound in, even in the guilt of
Chriſts blood, and to embrue their hands in it, as
<hi>Pilate</hi> the <hi>Romane</hi> Governour did by his <hi>ſentence,</hi> and
the <hi>Roman</hi> Souldiers by <hi>execution.</hi> And therefore we
find, <hi>Rev. 11. 8. Rome</hi> to be called <hi>the City where our
Lord was crucified;</hi> becauſe by the power and juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
of that State: that ſo the <hi>blood of all,</hi> yea even of
Chriſt himſelfe, <hi>might be found in her</hi> at her deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,
<hi>Revel. 18. ult.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to proceed in this Jewiſh ſtory. When <hi>our Lord</hi>
was <hi>aſcended,</hi> we reade <hi>Acts</hi> 4. that when <hi>Peter</hi> and
<hi>John were preaching to the people, the Prieſts and the
Captaine of the Temple, and the Sadduces came upon
them, ver. 1. and they laid hands on them, and put them in
hold, ver.</hi> 3. And then <hi>ver. 23. they being let goe</hi> (onely
with <hi>threatning to ſpeak no more in his name) they went to
their owne company,</hi> and there they went to Prayer:
and what doe they urge to God but the ſecond <hi>Pſal.</hi>
and ſpread that before him meerly upon this occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
that they were falne upon, and interrupted in his
worſhip, and threatned to preach no more in that
name, which they (being the relicts of Chriſt left
behinde him here) were to hold forth. They prayed
over <hi>with one accord</hi> the ſecond Pſalme, <hi>Lord thou art
God which haſt made heaven and earth, who by the mouth
of thy ſervant David haſt ſaid, Why did the heathen rage,
and the people imagine vaine things? The Kings of the
earth ſtood up, and the Rulers were gathered together againſt
the Lord and againſt his Chriſt. For of a truth, againſt thy
holy Child Jeſus,</hi> WHOM THOU HAST ANOINTED,
(and now anointed with the oyle of gladneſſe above
his fellowes) <hi>both Herod, and Pontius Pilate, with the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:159563:20"/>
Gentiles, and the people of Iſrael, were gathered together,
&amp;c.</hi> Theſe his Diſciples being his fellowes in his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointing,
did accordingly (as you here ſee) intereſt
their cauſe in his, by putting God in mind what they
did unto their Lord, in crucifying him, to provoke
him thereby to conſider what was now done to
themſelves, by the <hi>Rulers, Scribes, and Elders, Prieſts,
and Band of the Temple, ver.</hi> 1. 5.</p>
            <p>Well, ſtill the Jewes goe on, and follow the ſame
trade, as our Saviour Chriſt in <hi>Luke</hi> 21. 10, 11. fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told
his Diſciples that they ſhould; and withall, he
foretold them that there ſhould be <hi>wars</hi> upon this,
and <hi>commotions, Nation riſing againſt Nation, &amp;c.</hi> BE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FORE
ALL THESE (ſayes Chriſt) <hi>they ſhall lay their
hands on you, and perſecute you, delivering you up to the
Synagogues, and into priſon, being brought before Kings
and Rulers for my Names ſake.</hi> Our Saviour therein ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
that this perſecution of the Saints, ſhould be the
cauſe of all theſe wars; and ſo, of that Nations ruine,
as well as his owne death, (ſo involving his cauſe and
theirs together.) But they, as afore the warres, ſo
<hi>after the warres,</hi> and during the time of them, (Chriſt
ſayes) ſhould goe on and take no warning, this you
find in <hi>Mat. 24. 7, 8, 9. verſes</hi> compared, <hi>And this,</hi> ſayes
Chriſt there, <hi>ſhall be a teſtimony unto you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now that ſecond Pſalme (whither the Apoſtles
have brought us, and which the Apoſtles in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning
of the Goſpel prayed thus over, againſt
the Jewes) was by the holy Ghoſt intended againſt
all Nations and Kingdomes that ſhould in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
deal injuriouſly with the Saints, (as the Jews had
done with Chriſt) to the end of the world, ſo making
this inſtance the pattern and example to the reſt. In
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:159563:21"/>
the next words (if you read on) you find a ſolemne
inauguration of Chriſt, as King, now, when aſcended
into heaven, <hi>I have ſet my King on my holy hill,</hi> with a
Proclamation &amp; Declaration of Gods <hi>Decree,</hi> and great
Deſigne under the New Teſtament, to be effect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
and accompliſhed by this his new King ſet up,
I WILL DECLARE <hi>the</hi> DECRE. &amp;c. <hi>ver.</hi> 7. which
(as a Preface) refers to all that followes, and is in
effect no other then the ſame you have all this while
heard out of the Old. He gives Chriſt as a boone,
upon his Inauguration, all the Kingdoms of the world,
<hi>I will give thee</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the Heathen for thine inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,
and the utmoſt parts of the earth for thy poſſeſsion.</hi>
What to doe? Either to break them, or convert
them. <hi>Thou ſhalt bruiſe them with a rod of iron, and daſh
them in pieces like a potters veſſell:</hi> and this drift the
Apoſtles well knew, and therefore pertinently urged
it in their Prayer to God againſt the Jewes, which
Prayer of theirs had a concurrent influence into their
ruine. Now as the deſtruction of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> is made
by Chriſt the fore-running type of the end of the
world, ſo the deſtruction of that Nation for theſe
their doings to Chriſt and his Apoſtles and their fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers,
is an example to all Kingdomes that ſhall
doe the like afterwards unto the Saints: for which
Chriſt hath and will break them alſo. Therefore how
ends the Pſalme? BE WISE O YE KINGS, AND
INSTRVCTED YE JUDGES OF THE EARTH, &amp;c.
That is in effect, All ye <hi>States</hi> and <hi>Princes</hi> of the
world, learn to know this your INTEREST. Although
this might be enough in the generall, for the whole
<hi>New Teſtament:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet come we to the <hi>Roman Empire.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. The <hi>Romane</hi> Empire.</note> The Book of the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:159563:21"/>
               <hi>Revel.</hi> is a Propheſie of the deſtruction of that Empire,
either as Heatheniſh in the whole, or elſe when Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
(yet perſecuting then) in both the parts of it, <hi>Eaſt</hi>
and <hi>Weſt.</hi> That Book is a <hi>Tragy-Comedy,</hi> which begins
with a Kingdome given to be won by conqueſt<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Revel.</hi> 6. 8. When the ſeals begin to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, Chriſt <hi>goes forth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quering and to conquer.</hi>
               </note>, and
ends with the <hi>Coronation of a King,</hi> and the <hi>marriage
of his Bride:</hi> and all between, is but the removing
of all ſuch lets and impediments, namely, of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane
Monarchie, and all other Kingdoms which <hi>that</hi>
was broken into; ſo far as they ſtand in his way, and
poſſeſſe the roome of that Kingdome which he is to
ſet up. That this is one main argument of that Book,
I refer you to what that great and learned Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
Maſter <hi>Mede,</hi> hath largely opened.</p>
            <p>And herein Chriſt, when he firſt began (the whole
world then worſhipping Idols) had work enough to
doe. He ſets firſt upon conquering the whole <hi>Romane
Empire,</hi> as it was <hi>Heatheniſh,</hi> and the worſhip of Satan
and Idols in it, and in three hundred yeeres he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patcheth
that, and throwes downe all both <hi>Idoll<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worſhip,</hi>
and <hi>Princes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chap. 6.</note> that did uphold it. This the firſt
<hi>ſix ſeales</hi> doe ſhew. And then when the whole <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire</hi>
was turned <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> yet (as one well ſaid) <hi>the
devill did not turne Chriſtian:</hi> But under the name
and profeſſion of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> he ſtirreth up the <hi>Arrian
Chriſtian world</hi> to perſecute the <hi>Orthodox Chriſtians</hi>
as much as <hi>Heatheniſh Rome</hi> had done. But Chriſt
takes farther vengeance for this perſecution under
both theſe; <hi>Heatheniſh</hi> and <hi>Arrian Rome</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">It was the cry of the blood of the Saints ſlain underboth, that brought on them the ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed <hi>See</hi> Cha. 6. 10, 11.</note>. The Empire
having been divided afore into two parts; the <hi>Eaſtern</hi>
(all which now the Turk poſſeſſeth) and the <hi>Weſtern;</hi>
this in <hi>Europe:</hi> He falls firſt upon the <hi>Weſterne European</hi>
part, breaking that by the incurſion of thoſe barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:159563:22"/>
Nations the <hi>Goths</hi> and <hi>Vandalls;</hi> and this the
<hi>foure firſt trumpets</hi> doe ſound forth:<note place="margin">Chap. 8.</note> Then for the <hi>Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern</hi>
part of the Empire, (although his revenge was
ſlower, yet) he reſerved them to the ſoreſt vengeance
that could befall the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> world,<note place="margin">Chap: 9.</note> the conqueſt
and tyrannie of the <hi>Saracens</hi> firſt, and afterwards the
<hi>Turks,</hi> and theſe the <hi>fift</hi> and <hi>ſixt Trumpets</hi> ſucceſſively
held forth. Thus here is an end of the Roman Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchie
under the Emperours in the whole, and in
the parts of it.<note place="margin">Chap. 12.</note> The <hi>Weſterne</hi> part in <hi>Europe,</hi> was by
occaſion of the <hi>Goths</hi> invaſion, broken into <hi>ten</hi> King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes,
which though helping the woman againſt the
flood of <hi>Arrian</hi> perſecution, yet (through Satans ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing
of them) they ſet up the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> or <hi>Antichriſtian
Rome,</hi> and theſe all together did joyn together to make
as great a <hi>warre againſt the Saints</hi> in the 13.<note place="margin">Chap. 13.</note> Chapter,
as the Heathens and Arrians had done: And ſo Chriſt
was in a manner as farre off his Kingdome as at the
firſt. What then is the next great counter-plot of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus
Chriſt? It is to overcome theſe <hi>ten</hi> Kingdomes;
ſo you find, <hi>Revel. 17. 14. They ſhall</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>make
war with the Lambe, and the Lambe</hi> SHALL OVERCOME
THEM, <hi>for he is Lord of Lords, and King of Kings, and
they that are with him are called, and choſen, and faithfull.</hi>
The world, though turned Chriſtian, yet in all the
variations of it, goes on ſtill to perſecute the Saints;
For why? the <hi>world</hi> wil be the <hi>world</hi> ſtill, and
the <hi>Devill</hi> who is the <hi>Prince of the world,</hi> is the ſame
ſtill, and ſo he ſtill followes that trade he had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly
practiced, the ſame which you read of, <hi>Chap.</hi>
12. <hi>ver.</hi> 17. even to <hi>make war</hi> with <hi>the remnant of the
womans ſeed,</hi> which <hi>keep the commandements of God, and
have the teſtimony of Jeſus.</hi> This is his deſigne, and let
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:159563:22"/>
the world turn never ſo much, and refine as much as
it will, Satan endeavours ſtill to forme a party up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
them, whom he turns againſt the Saints, (or
ſome of the Saints) for that is the great intereſt of his
Kingdome, (as that place ſhews) it is more to perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute
the Saints, then to carry men on to ſinne. And
he will be content to fall but upon a few ſometimes,
rather then be put out of this his trade. And
therefore now beſides plain <hi>Popery</hi> which is prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyed
of in 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. to ariſe in the <hi>latter dayes:</hi> You
have in 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 1. another Propheſie of a ſort of
men that ſhall ariſe in the LAST DAYES, (Popery is
Prophecyed of to be in the <hi>latter dayes) who,</hi> ſhall have
<hi>a forme of godlineſſe, and be deſpiſers of them that are good:</hi>
Thus the Devil hath carryed on his deſign Age after
Age, and Jeſus Chriſt purſues more cloſely his great
deſigne alſo, and will never leave till he hath over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come:
And HE SHALL OVERCOME, <hi>for He is the
King of Kings, and thoſe that are with him are called cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen
and faithfull.</hi> And all this (if it were not the ſcope
of that Booke of the <hi>Revelation</hi>) yet ſtory would
make good. Why ſhould I inſtance in more? you
know the <hi>little ſtone,</hi> Chriſt and his Saints, ſhall <hi>daſh
all in pieces, Dan.</hi> 2. But enough.</p>
            <p>You have heard the truth of this point exemplified
by all theſe inſtances. As for <hi>Reaſons</hi> of it, the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
affords a farre greater plenty then of <hi>Inſtances:</hi>
and in many of the inſtances given, you may finde
Reaſons adjoyned by God himſelfe: as here in the
Text, they are <hi>Gods anointed;</hi> in that example of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypts
overthrow, Gods <hi>firſt-borne;</hi> in that of Babels,
'twas the vengeance of <hi>Gods Temple,</hi> and ſo on. The
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:159563:23"/>
time will give me leave to ſingle out but a very few
of many. The Doctrine was this, <hi>That the greateſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt
of all States and Princes, lyes in their uſage of the
Saints; to deale ill or well with them, is that whereon their
miſery or welfare doth depend.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One <hi>reaſon</hi> of it is,<note place="margin">1. Reaſon.</note> (that which ſhould indeed have
been my firſt <hi>Obſervation</hi> out of the Text, <hi>viz.) The
neereneſſe and dearneſſe of the Saints to God.</hi> You ſee how
tender he is of them, TOUCH <hi>them not.</hi> If you would
underſtand the tenderneſſe of Gods heart expreſſed
in that word, parallel it with that, <hi>He that</hi> TOUCHETH
<hi>them, toucheth the</hi> APPLE OF MINE EYE: and you
have the expreſſion twice. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 17. 8. and <hi>Zech.</hi> 2. 8. there
is nothing more deare then the eye: <hi>you would have
pulled out your eyes,</hi> ſayes <hi>Paul:</hi> and of the eye, the
<hi>pupa,</hi> the <hi>black</hi> of the eye moſt. When the <hi>Ammonites</hi>
required of <hi>the men of Jabeſh Gilead,</hi> that they ſhould
thruſt out all their <hi>right eyes, 1 Sam.</hi> 11. 2. the Text
ſaith, <hi>ver.</hi> 6. that when <hi>Saul</hi> heard of it, <hi>the Spirit of
God came upon him, and his anger was greatly kindled,</hi>
and he went and cut them off, and ſcattered them,
ſo that <hi>not two of them were left together.</hi> If <hi>Saul</hi> their
King, a tyrannicall King, was thus moved for this
offer of an injury to the eyes of his Subjects, much
more God for thoſe, who are to him as his own eye,
yea as the apple of it. Or if you will have this Reaſon
in an expreſſion more neerely akin to the doctrine it
ſelfe, <hi>they are dearer to God then Nations</hi> ſimply conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered:
the reaſon is ſtrong, That therefore, the <hi>Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt</hi>
of all Nations muſt needs lye in theſe <hi>Saints. Eſay</hi>
43. 3, 4. <hi>I gave Egypt for thy ranſome, Ethiopia and Seba
for thee, ſince thou waſt precious in my ſight, thou
haſt been honourable, and I have loved thee, therefore
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:159563:23"/>
will I give men for thee, and people for thy life.</hi>
Thus he valued them under the Old Teſtament. But
did he give Nations for them then? They have coſt
him more <hi>ſince,</hi> they have coſt him the blood of his
<hi>Sonne: He that ſpared not his owne</hi> Sonne, <hi>but delivered
him up for us: how ſhall he not with him freely give us</hi>
ALL THINGS? <hi>Rom. 8. 32. All things are theirs,
the world, &amp;c. becauſe they are Chriſts.</hi> Look what rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
the Old Teſtament gives of this point in hand,
from their neereneſſe to God, the New Teſtament
uſeth the ſame. <hi>They are my firſt borne,</hi> ſaid God to the
Kingdome of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and therefore <hi>I will take away thy
firſt-borne:</hi> The New Teſtament ſpeaks the ſame;
they are the <hi>Church of the firſt-borne, written in heaven,
Heb.</hi> 12. 23. Was it the <hi>vengeance of the Temple</hi> was
<hi>Babels</hi> overthrow? the New Teſtament utters the
ſame, and to the ſame purpoſe, <hi>If any man deſtroyes the
Temple of God, him ſhall God deſtroy:</hi> FOR THE TEM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PLE
OF GOD IS HOLY, <hi>which Temple are</hi> YE, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi>
3. 17. Againe, <hi>Iſrael</hi> is <hi>Holineſſe to the Lord, the firſt
fruits of his encreaſe,</hi> and <hi>therefore all that devoure him
ſhall offend,</hi> (offend greatly) <hi>and evill ſhall come upon
them, ſaith the Lord, Jer.</hi> 2. 3. Thus ſpeaks the Old
Teſtament. The ſame reaſon and expreſſions are gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
you ſee in the New, <hi>The Temple of God</hi> IS HOLY,
and they are <hi>the</hi> FIRST FRUITS <hi>of all his creatures,
Jam. 1. 18. Theſe are the redeemed from among men, and
the</hi> FIRST FRUITS <hi>to God and the Lambe,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
prevaile, <hi>Revel.</hi> 14. 4.</p>
            <p>And as becauſe they are thus deare to God, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
if they be dealt ill withall, it is the cauſe of the
ruine of a Nation: ſo on the contrary likewiſe, if a
Nation deale well with them, it is a cauſe of his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:159563:24"/>
upon them; Yea he doth give Nations and States
their being for their ſakes. <hi>They are a bleſsing in the
midſt of the land, Eſay</hi> 19. 24. In ſo much as God
ſpareth the <hi>tree</hi> for a ſmall <hi>bunch of grapes,</hi> (ſo he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pareth
his people in reſpect of the reſt of a Nation)
<hi>Deſtroy it not, for there is a bleſsing in it, Eſay</hi> 65. 8. or
rather as the ſame <hi>Eſay,</hi> they are to the whole tree,
(the Nation they live in) what the <hi>pith,</hi> the <hi>heart,</hi> the
<hi>ſubſtance</hi> is. <hi>As an oke whoſe ſubſtance is in them when they
caſt their leaves, ſo the</hi> HOLY SEED (the Saints) <hi>ſhall
be the</hi> SUBSTANCE OF IT. <hi>Eſay 6. ult.</hi> That pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves
life in a Nation, when the branches of it
are hewne, or it <hi>caſt its leaves.</hi> Theſe things are
ſpoken in relation to their being the cauſe of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation
of a nation in both theſe places. Saints that
are as ſtrangers to a Nation, and onely make it their
refuge, yet their preſence is in ſuch a caſe a preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
to them. <hi>Moab,</hi> (ſayes God) <hi>Let mine out-caſts
dwell with thee, and be thou a covert to them,</hi> Eſay 16. 4.
And <hi>ver. 5. And in mercy ſhall the throne be eſtabliſhed.</hi>
But much more NATIVE Saints procure this
bleſſing, their relation being nearer and dearer;
<hi>Of Sion it ſhall be ſaid, This and that man was</hi> BORN <hi>in
her;</hi> And what followes? <hi>The higheſt himſelfe ſhall
eſtabliſh her, Pſal.</hi> 87. 3.</p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">2. Reaſon.</note> another reaſon is taken from the great
intereſt the Saints have in God the Governour, and
the priviledge which themſelves have vouchſafed
them by God, in ruling and governing this world,
and the providences of God therein. They are <hi>Privy
Counſellors</hi> to the great <hi>King of Kings,</hi> who governs
all the States and Kingdomes in the world; and God
doth give theſe his Saints a <hi>Commiſsion</hi> to ſet up and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:159563:24"/>
pull down by their prayers and interceſſions. The Old
Teſtament ſpeakes in a high language, in <hi>Eſay</hi> 45.
11. (I might have quoted it before, for it comes in as
the reaſon of Gods ſetting up <hi>Cyrus</hi> for his peoples
ſake) <hi>Aske me of things to come concerning my ſonnes, and
concerning the</hi> WORK OF MY HANDS COMMAND
YE ME. Who ſpeaks this? The words afore, are,
<hi>Thus</hi> SAITH <hi>the Lord, the holy One of Iſrael, and his
Maker.</hi> It would have been blaſphemie for us to have
ſaid it, but that the Lord himſelfe firſt hath <hi>ſaid</hi> it,
and given them this priviledge, <hi>Concerning the work
of my hands command ye me.</hi> And which makes it the
more obſervable, before he doth in this place menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned
confer this honour and priviledge upon them,
he firſt (as on purpoſe) minds them of that infinite
diſtance and diſproportion betwixt himſelf and them,
(ſo to put the more wonder upon it) he tells them,
<hi>ver.</hi> 9, 10. that they were but the <hi>clay,</hi> he the <hi>Potter,</hi>
that could not (therefore <hi>of right</hi>) ſay ſo much unto
him about his matters, as <hi>Why madeſt thou me thus?</hi>
Yet behold, I that am thus <hi>your Maker,</hi> give you leave
to diſpoſe by your prayers the <hi>great works of my hands,</hi>
which concerne my <hi>children,</hi> my <hi>ſonnes,</hi> the affaires
of Kingdoms, even ſo far as they relate to their good.
And he ſpeaks it upon this occaſion, that for their
ſakes he had raiſed up <hi>Cyrus,</hi> and pulled downe the
Babylonian Monarchy, becauſe they by their prayers
had ſought this. They are ſaid elſewhere to <hi>decree a
thing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 22. 28.</note> ſo <hi>Job,</hi> and <hi>to bring it to paſſe,</hi> and God is ſaid to
<hi>fulfill their counſels.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 20.</note> And this intereſt they have either
for good or evill to the nations they live in. Firſt,
for <hi>evill.</hi> Thus <hi>Revel.</hi> 11. 6. the <hi>two Witneſſes have po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer
to ſmite the earth with plagues as oft as they will: And
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:159563:25"/>
if any man</hi> WILL <hi>hurt them, in</hi> THIS MANNER <hi>he
ſhall be killed,</hi> that is, with the higheſt and ſoreſt
vengeance, and God <hi>avengeth them ſpeedily, Luke</hi>
18. 8. And ſo for <hi>bleſsing, The innocent delivers the
Iſland through the pureneſſe of his hands, Job</hi> 22. 30. Thus
one righteous <hi>Lot</hi> was (for the preſent) the cauſe of
the reſcue of the Sodomites, the wickedeſt people
in the world, and afterwards ordained to the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt
judgement.</p>
            <p>A third reaſon,<note place="margin">3. Reaſon.</note> is, the INTEREST of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi>
himſelfe. And to ſhew that he is <hi>King,</hi> even <hi>King
of Kings,</hi> and hath a Kingdom ordained to him and
his Saints, ſupreame to all theirs, in the meane while,
his deſign and practice is, and hath been, to break all
Kingdoms that do oppoſe him, or oppreſſe his Saints.
This reaſon I might enlarge out of <hi>Daniel, The God of
heaven ſhall ſet up a Kingdome which ſhall break in pieces
and conſume all theſe Kingdomes, but it ſhall ſtand for ever,
Cha.</hi> 2. 44. and <hi>Chap.</hi> 7. but I ſhall inſiſt (in this Head of
Reaſons) onely upon that eminent title of Chriſts,
(which holds forth this his INTEREST) that he is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titled
KING OF SAINTS, <hi>Rev.</hi> 15. 3. which title is
there given him, as in relation to the ſetting up his
<hi>Worſhip,</hi> ſo to the overthrowing and overcomming
the Nations that doe oppoſe his Saints, and this by
the ſeven <hi>Vialls</hi> which their prayers have filled. And
at that time (it is likewiſe there ſaid) he doth <hi>marvel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous
works,</hi> being <hi>King of Saints.</hi> In the <hi>Old Teſtament</hi>
he is called <hi>the King of Nations,</hi> (though he was <hi>King
of Saints</hi> alſo then) ſo <hi>Jer.</hi> 10. 7. and he gave demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration
of it to purpoſe, by ſetting up that one Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of the Jews, which he had choſen of all nations,
that <hi>that</hi> one nation ſhould ruine all the nations round
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:159563:25"/>
about them: for he was peculiarly their <hi>King,</hi> and the
King of all thoſe other nations alſo. But now he hath
ſcattered his Saints in and through all nations, (<hi>Thou
haſt redeemed us out of all Nations,</hi> that is the language
of the New Teſtament) he is therefore therein called
<hi>King of Saints:</hi> he carrying on the ſame deſigne by
thoſe Saints, which he did before, and is as able to
make it good, he being no leſſe <hi>King of Nations</hi> ſtill, or
<hi>Lord Almighty,</hi> (as you have it in that fore-cited
place.) And he being thus peculiarly <hi>their King,</hi> his
intereſt is to maintaine, defend, and take part with
them againſt all thoſe that doe maligne them, as he
did the nation of the Jews. It is his title, and his moſt
royall title, and the greateſt title, that he is <hi>King of
Saints;</hi> he preferreth it to his title of being <hi>King of
Nations;</hi> that vaniſheth, and is not mentioned in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon.
This therefore anſwerably muſt be his grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt
intereſt, which of all other he now purſueth. And
therefore if all thoſe Nations in which his Saints
are, doe not bow to it, and comply with it, he will
ſhew himſelfe that he is <hi>King of Saints,</hi> and of <hi>Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi>
alſo, by ruining of them. As the greateſt intereſt
of the <hi>Devils</hi> Kingdome is to <hi>perſecute thoſe that keep
the commandements of Jeſus,</hi> ſo it is the greateſt intereſt
of the Kingdome of Jeſus Chriſt to preſerve his
Saints, and to confound thoſe that injure them, for
he is <hi>the King of Saints.</hi> And further, in the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
when this his Kingdome was farther off, and
longer to come, and yet you have ſeene how ſtrongly
he drove on this deſigne then; but in the <hi>New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament</hi>
he is aſcended, and perſonally as <hi>Man</hi> inveſted
into it: <hi>We ſee Jeſus crowned with glory and honour,</hi>
(ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. whoſe faith was as reall in
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:159563:26"/>
this as our ſight can be) and he SITS there EXPECT<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ING,
as thinking the time long, <hi>till alll his enemies are
ſubdued, Heb.</hi> 10. 13. which the ſame Apoſtle elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where
interpreteth, (and therein ſpeaks home to the
point in hand) the putting downe <hi>all rule and dominion</hi>
that are oppoſite to his Saints, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 24, 25.
verſes compared. And accordingly in all thoſe
Pſalmes, where ever his aſcenſion and inveſtiture
into his Kingdome at Gods right hand is prophecy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
of, there the ruine or converſion of Kings and
Kingdomes are alſo ſpoken and prophecyed of.
Reade <hi>Pſalm. 2. Pſalm. 68. Pſal.</hi> 110. And let me adde
this to all, That as the <hi>ſhorter time</hi> Satan hath, the
more is his <hi>rage;</hi> ſo the ſhorter time Chriſt hath,
and the nearer he is to the poſſeſſion of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
the more is his zeale for his Saints, and indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation
againſt his enemies. His heart is ſet upon it,
and the more eager doth his deſire become every
day to attaine his long expected Kingdome, and to
throw donwe all that oppoſe it: and therefore it is
that we ſee in this latter age, he hath made ſuch
changes in the world. We have ſeen him doe that
in a few yeeres, that he hath not done in an hundred
yeeres before; for he being <hi>King of Nations,</hi> and <hi>King
of Saints,</hi> he purſues his intereſt; and being more neere
his <hi>Kingdome, he takes it with violence.</hi> We are now
within the whirle of it, therefore his motions are
rapt. Hence therefore all States and Kingdoms had
need now (of all times elſe) <hi>to be inſtructed;</hi> and
accordingly comply with this <hi>intereſt</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> it is
more eſpecially now then ever their greateſt intereſt.
It is well for us, that Jeſus Chriſt he is our <hi>King,</hi>
who is the <hi>King of Kings,</hi> and <hi>King of Saints:</hi> and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:159563:26"/>
withall that he is ſo neere the enjoyment of his
Kingdome.</p>
            <div type="application">
               <head>APPLICATION.</head>
               <p>I Shall come now to a word of <hi>Application,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Application.</note> which
I ſhall diſpatch exceeding briefly. In thoſe fore-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſed
inſtances I have carryed you over, and given
you a proſpect of all Kingdomes throughout the
ſtory of the Bible, and at laſt I brought you, and
ſet you downe, and left you in the times of theſe
<hi>Tenne</hi> Kingdomes of <hi>Europe,</hi> of which the holy
Ghoſt hath prophecyed, <hi>Revelat. 17. 14. Theſe</hi>
(ſaith he) <hi>ſhall make war with the Lambe, and the Lambe
ſhall overcome them, for he is Lord of Hoſts, and King of
Kings, and they that are with him, are called, and choſen,
and faithfull.</hi> And it is certaine, we are in the laſt
times of theſe kingdoms, and we all here live in one of
them. But a word of <hi>Encouragement</hi> and <hi>Direction</hi> to
thoſe of this kingdome.</p>
               <p>You have heard in thoſe words I laſt read,<note place="margin">1. Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> the
greateſt ſecurity that any kingdoms can have in theſe
times: for firſt, in the generall, this Text holds forth
plainly, that Jeſus Chriſt by vertue of his being <hi>King
of Kings,</hi> and being <hi>King of Saints,</hi> (as you heard even
now) he will <hi>overcome,</hi> and ſubdue theſe kingdomes
to himſelfe, and yet (for our encouragement) not ſo
as to deſtroy them; why? Becauſe theſe kingdoms,
as ſuch, ſhall deſtroy the whore: and therefore ſhall
not be <hi>overcome</hi> by way of <hi>deſolation,</hi> but by way of a
more happy conqueſt of <hi>Reformation</hi> and <hi>Converſion:</hi>
Thus the Text ſeems cleerly to ſpeak; <hi>for the ten horns,</hi>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:159563:27"/>
(which are theſe ten kingdomes) <hi>ſhall hate the whore,
and make her deſolate, and burne her with fire, ver.</hi> 16. As
I have therefore thought this Text to be a barre to
the projected <hi>Spaniſh Monarchy,</hi> over them, even then
when it was in the greateſt height, and in moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability
to have carryed it; ſo the greateſt ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
for continuance and preſervation of theſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes,
becauſe they muſt remaine <hi>tenne Kings,</hi>
or ſupreame States and kingdomes, untill the
whore is burnt, for they muſt deſtroy her. And
firſt, for their number, <hi>Ten:</hi> tis true, they have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed
been more, yet never fewer, ſince the brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
of the Romane Empire. And when it is ſaid
<hi>ten</hi> KINGS, it is not neceſſarily to be underſtood
there ſhould be ſo many Monarchs alwayes, (in a
ſtrict ſenſe as we uſe the phraſe) for in the language
of this Book, <hi>Kings</hi> is put for <hi>Supreame States.</hi> Thus
<hi>Rome</hi> is ſaid to have had <hi>ſeven Kings,</hi> and yet five
of thoſe Governments were not Monarchicall. Theſe
kingdomes may fall one upon another, there may
be civill broyles, and diviſions, and diſtractions,
and thereby they may be ſorely puniſht as wee
have beene, for dealing ill with the Saints. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
two may be joyned into one, and one may
be broken into two, ſo they have varied in ſeverall
times and ages, yet ſtill they have ſtood, and at the
leaſt the number of <hi>Ten</hi> hath beene kept up: and
though they have made warre againſt the <hi>Lambe,</hi> and
have been puniſht for ſo doing, yet the Lambe ſhall
overcome them another way then by deſtroying
them, even by winning ground upon them: ſo as
where you ſee Jeſus Chriſt hath took footing in any
one of theſe kingdomes by ſuch a way of conqueſt,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:159563:27"/>
(as in ours he hath done a ſecond time for double ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity)
ſtand that Kingdome ſhall till you ſee <hi>Rome</hi>
downe.</p>
               <p>Now the next thing I deſire you to take notice of
in the words, is the <hi>Reaſon</hi> why that Chriſt will thus
overcome them, and preſerve them. FOR (ſayes
ſayes the holy Ghoſt) <hi>thoſe that are with him,</hi> (name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
in theſe ten kingdomes, and ſo members there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of)
are <hi>called, and faithfull, and choſen.</hi> Therefore it
is that the Lambe ſhall work theſe kingdomes about,
and win ground upon them, and ſhall cauſe them at
length to hate the whore, and therefore they ſhall
ſtand till the whore be ruined, and how long after, he
onely knowes that hath ſet them up.</p>
               <p>It hath been one great outward evidence to my
faith, of the truth of the New Teſtament, that what
was in this particular foretold in this Book ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly
ſhould ſo come to paſſe as we ſee it hath done.
When <hi>John</hi> wrote this Propheſie, there were none
of all theſe kingdomes ſet up, the Empire was not
broken. You ſee the Empire hath been broken into
theſe kingdomes, and they have given their power to
the beaſt: and we know how rooted the power of the
<hi>beaſt</hi> once was in all theſe <hi>Kingdomes,</hi> ſo as, who could
<hi>make war with the beaſt?</hi> yet we have likewiſe ſeene
<hi>the Lamb hath overcome</hi> many of them, eſpecially theſe
<hi>Northern</hi> Kingdomes, where he hath ſet up his Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.
He hath overcome them, and he wins ground
upon us every day, and works us up age after age
to a farther Reformation, to more light and holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
and ſo he will doe till he hath perfectly over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
every Popiſh principle out of them. Wee
ſee all this done, we ſee likewiſe all theſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:159563:28"/>
ſtand, and not ſubdued to any one Civill
Monarchie over them all: We ſee <hi>Rome</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied
of in this Book<note n="*" place="margin">Revel. 17. 18.</note>, yet ſtanding and poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
ſome of theſe kingdomes. We ſee likewiſe mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes
of <hi>faithfull called and choſen,</hi> whom God hath
raiſed up in theſe kingdomes to oppoſe the <hi>Whore.</hi>
All theſe things we have ſeen fulfilled, therefore I
beleve this ſhall be fulfilled too, that theſe kingdoms
ſhall ſtill continue, where God hath <hi>faithfull, called,</hi>
and <hi>choſen,</hi> and that they ſhall be the ruine of the <hi>whore</hi>
in the end. Having ſeen and beleeved ſo far, we may
very well truſt him for the reſt. This for the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall.</p>
               <p>More particularly, to you of this Kingdome wee
live in: If you would yet know and be confirmed in
what is your greateſt <hi>intereſt,</hi> this Text ſpeaks more
punctually to the point, and it holds forth by way of
Propheſie thus much to you, that your intereſt lyes
(as you are one of theſe ten Kindomes) in what I
have hitherto told you, even in YOUR <hi>faithfull,
called, and choſen.</hi> And let me ſpeak this for your pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar
encouragement farther: That look as where
God doth give a command with a reaſon, upon
whom the reaſon falls moſt ſtrongly, there is the
greateſt obligation; ſo where God gives a promiſe,
and gives it with a reaſon, where moſt of the reaſon
is found true, there certainly the promiſe will take
place moſt in the fulfilling of it. Now upon what hath
hee put the ſtanding of theſe kingdomes, and their
being thus <hi>overcome by the Lambe,</hi> and that they ſhall
<hi>hate the whore,</hi> ſo as to deſtroy her in the end? It ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
you ſee in this, that they that <hi>are with the
Lambe,</hi> are <hi>faithfull, called,</hi> and <hi>choſen.</hi> Hee puts
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:159563:28"/>
the very reaſon of it upon this, <hi>The Lambe ſhall over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
them,</hi> FOR (ſaith he) <hi>they that are with him, are
called, and choſen, and faithfull.</hi> Now look upon this
Iſle in which we live, and it is the richeſt Ship, that
hath the moſt of the precious jewels of our Lord and
Saviour Jeſus Chriſt in it, and the greateſt treaſure,
of any kingdome in the world, I had well-nigh ſaid,
as all the world beſides. Now where there are moſt
of <hi>called, choſen,</hi> and <hi>faithfull,</hi> certainly there (towards
the time of <hi>Romes</hi> ruine) the Promiſe will take the
moſt effect. Here then lyes your INTEREST. You
have it not onely confirmed from the generall truth
of that great point I have all this while been giving
demonſtrations of, but further you have it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed
by a more ſpeciall charter of promiſe and
propheſie (which you may well beleeve, having
ſeen ſo much of it fulfilled) granted forth to theſe
kingdoms long before their erection. And as for
this Kingdome, give mee leave upon this ſo juſt
and ſolemne an occaſion, to take the boldneſſe to ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
this in the ſame expreſſion which now well-nigh
twenty yeeres agoe I uſed in publique, That if we
had ſtood at Gods elbow when he <hi>bounded out the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi>
and <hi>appointed the times and ſeaſons</hi> that men
ſhould live in, (as the Apoſtle ſpeaks) we ſhould not
have known (unleſſe when Chriſt himſelfe was alive,
and the Apoſtles, in thoſe Primitive times, unleſſe
in <hi>Judea</hi> it ſelfe, where all the Apoſtles were together)
in what age, or in what place, in what nation or king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
we would have choſen to have lived in, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect
of the enjoyment of the Goſpel, and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion
of Saints, more then in this kingdome where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
we live. Other Churches they have had the glory
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:159563:29"/>
of Reformation, and have had the honour in the firſt
age of Reformation; but we though in that reſpect
have been like to <hi>bleare-ey'd Leah,</hi> yet have ſince beene
abundantly the more fruitfull of <hi>Saints, faithfull, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,
and choſen.</hi> This is therefore our great ſecurity, and
it is the more ſpeciall intereſt of this Kingdome in
which we live, the <hi>Magna Charta</hi> of it.</p>
               <p>And therefore that which I ſhall make fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
bold with your leave and patience is but
onely this,<note place="margin">2. Direction.</note> to adde a word of <hi>Exhortation</hi> and <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection</hi>
to MAINTAINE THIS INTEREST,
and to <hi>preſerve it.</hi> To this end, conſider, it is not ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply
having Saints, and multitudes of Saints, <hi>called,
faithfull,</hi> and <hi>choſen,</hi> but it is the uſing them <hi>kindly,</hi>
and <hi>dealing well</hi> with them, that is the intereſt of a
Nation. <hi>Judea</hi> it ſelfe had the beſt of Saints, it had
<hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and multitudes of others alſo
in that Countrey, (which were afterwards diſperſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
all <hi>Nations</hi>) yet though they had theſe multitudes,
becauſe they dealt unkindly with them, it was their
ruine, and God provided a ſafety for thoſe his Saints,
by diſperſing them into all Nations, through their
perſecution of them.</p>
               <p>That worthy <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Rohan,</hi> that writ that Book of
the CIVILL INTEREST OF THE STATES OF
EUROPE, in his <hi>Preface</hi> to it, ſayes, That <hi>according
as the proper</hi> INTEREST <hi>of each hath been well or ill fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed,
it hath cauſed the ruine of ſome, the greatneſſe of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</hi>
That which that worthy Duke thus ſpeaketh
of the Civill <hi>Intereſt,</hi> give me leave, from all the
grounds forementioned, to preſſe upon you concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
that which is your greateſt intereſt; an <hi>intereſt</hi>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:159563:29"/>
moſt divine, moſt generall, and fundamentall. <hi>The
Saints of England are the Intereſt of England;</hi> look to,
and keep to this your intereſt, namely, <hi>maintaine</hi>
and <hi>preſerve</hi> the <hi>Saints</hi> among you, and make provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
for them, as you would preſerve the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.
When afterwards the ſame Author parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly
comes to ſpeak of the proper intereſt of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
he hath a ſaying, (and he ſeems to ſpeak it as if
it had been an <hi>Aphroiſme</hi> of the late Queens) that
<hi>England is a mighty Animal, which can never die except
it kill it ſelfe.</hi> To follow his Maxime in that
alſo, wee may apply it to this intereſt in hand.
There is a <hi>mighty</hi> body, and company of Saints
in this Kingdome. Now if they could all be united
in one, and their diviſions and animoſities allayed, and
all reconciled and made one, I am confident we need
not feare if all the Nations of the world were gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
together round about us. <hi>But if ye bite and devoure
one another, take heed ye be not conſumed one of another.</hi> It
is a State Maxime as well as a Church rule, there is
nothing elſe can deſtroy us.</p>
               <p>If any man think I am a pleading for a liberty of
all opinions, of what nature and how groſſe ſoever, I
humbly deſire them to remember that I onely plead
for Saints, and I anſwer plainly, <hi>The Saints they need it
not.</hi> The Apoſtle tels us that there are <hi>damnable here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies,</hi>
ſo 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 1, 2. and they will ſoone unſaint men;
there are errors that are <hi>capitall, not holding the head,</hi> ſo
<hi>Col.</hi> 2. Do but diſtinguiſh theſe from others, &amp; let this
be one foundation laid for this union. And when I
ſay <hi>Saints,</hi> I mean no one party of men: Doe we not
know that the <hi>new creature</hi> is found in <hi>circumciſion</hi> and
in <hi>uncircumciſion,</hi> and as eminent in the one as in the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:159563:30"/>
other? and it were the higheſt ſacriledge in the world
to ingroſſe that title of <hi>Saints</hi> and the <hi>godly party</hi> to any
one. Characters of Saints I need not give you, it hath
been the main ſubject of the preaching in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
for theſe forty yeeres and upwards, to deſcribe
them to you, and diſtinguiſh men from men.</p>
               <p>As there are multitudes of <hi>faithfull, called,</hi> and <hi>cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen
ones</hi> in this Kingdome, ſo you, Honourable and
worthy Senatours, are the <hi>called,</hi> and <hi>choſen,</hi> out of all
theſe, to this great work, and have <hi>obtained mercy</hi> from
our God, to be in a great meaſure <hi>faithfull.</hi> Conſider
the truſt God hath committed to you. You have the
richeſt treaſury that I know God hath above ground
elſewhere on earth. THE SAINTS OF ENGLAND
ARE THE INTEREST OF ENGLAND. Write this
upon your walls, to have it in your eye in all your
conſultations, never to ſwerve from it for any other
intereſt whatſoever.</p>
               <p>And have reſpect to the Saints, and to the whole
lump of them; if you will maintaine your intereſt
whole and intire: have regard to the Saints SMALL
and GREAT. You ſhall often finde that expreſſion,
as in <hi>Revel. 11. 18. When the Kingdomes of the world be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came
the Kingdomes of Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>Revel.</hi> 19. when the
<hi>whore is judged, ver.</hi> 2. it is ſaid, <hi>that all the Saints</hi> SMALL
<hi>and</hi> GREAT <hi>rejoyced. ver.</hi> 5. 7. What vow doth <hi>David</hi>
make when he ſhould obtaine the Kingdome?<note place="margin">Pſal. 101 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Mine
eyes ſhall be upon</hi> THE FAITHFULL OF THE
LAND, <hi>that they may dwell with me.</hi> Let yours be ſo.</p>
               <p>You are the ſhields of the earth, under God, and
for his Saints: as in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 47. The <hi>ſhield</hi> ſhould defend
the whole body, and all the parts and members of it.
You are <hi>covering Cherubims</hi> unto the Arke of God,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:159563:30"/>
(ſo the Prince of <hi>Tyre</hi> is called, <hi>Ezech.</hi> 28. 16.) ſtretch
your wings from one end of the holy of holies to the
other, ſo as to cover all. You are the nailes of the
Temple, and for the veſſels thereof, as <hi>Eliakim, Iſa.</hi>
22. 24. is called a <hi>naile,</hi> on which ALL the <hi>veſſels</hi>
ſhould be hung, and by whom alike ſupported, the
<hi>veſſels of</hi> SMALL <hi>quantity,</hi> as well as great, <hi>from the
veſſels of cups</hi> even <hi>to all the veſſels of flagons,</hi> ſo the
Prophet there ſpeaks, comparing the people of God
to the veſſels of the Sanctuary, and <hi>ſmall</hi> weak Saints
to the veſſels of <hi>ſmaller</hi> quantity, and the <hi>ſtronger</hi> to
the <hi>greater:</hi> and <hi>Eliakim</hi> to a nayle, and a like ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port
to all. <hi>Shebna</hi> his Predeceſſour had been an
oppreſſor of the Saints, and therefore God ſayes of
him, that he ſhould be <hi>driven from his ſtation,</hi> and <hi>cut</hi>
or <hi>ſawn</hi> off from the wall, ſo as the wall ſhould ſtand:
and he would put <hi>Eliakim</hi> in his roome, and <hi>hang all
the Saints upon him.</hi> You are <hi>Mordecai's,</hi> and it is ſaid
of him in <hi>Heſt.</hi> 10. 3. that <hi>He was accepted of the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude
of his brethren, ſeeking the wealth of his people, and
ſpeaking peace to</hi> ALL <hi>his ſeed.</hi> You are likewiſe called
<hi>Shepherds;</hi> now the Shepherds are to take care of all
the ſheep. Oh ſee that all the ſheep be folded, and have
paſtures to lie down in: not only a <hi>ſtaffe</hi> and a <hi>rod,</hi> but
<hi>folds &amp; paſtures for them:</hi> take care not of the <hi>ſtrong</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
but of the <hi>ſick</hi> and the <hi>diſeaſed,</hi> ſo the expreſſion is,
<hi>Ezek.</hi> 34. 21. thoſe that are ſick and diſeaſed, <hi>that men
did puſh with their hornes till they were ſcattered abroad,</hi>
not onely reduce them from their <hi>ſcatterings in a darke
and a cloudy day,</hi> as <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34. 13, 14. but <hi>feed them in a
good fold,</hi> and <hi>judge betwixt them, and thoſe that would puſh
them.</hi> You are <hi>Fathers,</hi> and you ſhould ſee <hi>proviſion</hi>
made for all the children; and though they through
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:159563:31"/>
way wardneſſe will not eate together, yet let them
not ſtarve.</p>
               <p>And to conclude, let me uſe your own word to you,
UNITE, or (if you will, the Apoſtles) <hi>Reconcile</hi> all the
Saints in this Kingdome together. Providence hath
diſpoſed it ſo, that they doe and will differ in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.
The Apoſtles, who were Oracles infallible,
could not in their times wholly prevent it. And dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering
thus in judgement, they will hardly ever of
themſelves agree. But it is your work, and will be
your honour, to make them and to cauſe them ſo to
doe, and to finde out wayes whereby this may be
done, notwithſtanding theſe their differences. Thus
<hi>Conſtantine</hi> dealt as a Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciler
amongſt his <hi>Divines,</hi> and
he did it with ſucceſſe. It is
of all works the happyeſt and
moſt glorious,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lege</hi> Euſebium <hi>in vita</hi> Conſtantini, <hi>lib. 3. c.</hi> 13. Ipſe conſilio interfuit, <hi>reconciliavit</hi> eos qui <hi>diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debant,</hi> &amp; ad concordiam perſuaſit: Eos qui pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo inſolentiores &amp; ferociores fuerunt, mitigavit; nec antea deſi it, quàm omnes ad concordiam re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vecaverit, &amp; tum hanc quaſi <hi>SECUNDAM VICTORIAM</hi> nactu<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Feſtum Triumphale celebravit. <hi>Whitak. contr. 3. quaeſt.</hi> 4.</note> for it was Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus
Chriſt his eminent work.
<hi>Eph. 2. 14. He is our</hi> PEACE,
<hi>who hath made both one, and hath broken downe the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
wall between us, having aboliſh in his fleſh the enmity:</hi>
and a greater enmity was betwixt Jews and Gentiles,
then among us. He did it by his blood; doe you min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle
his blood with faith, and mingle therewith but
the Rules given by the Apoſtles, by which they ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected
this, as in <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. when one <hi>beleeved that he
might eate all things,</hi> another that was <hi>weake</hi> durſt not,
but eate <hi>hearbs, ver. 2. Let not him that eateth,</hi> ſayes he
in this caſe, <hi>deſpiſe him that eateth not; and let not him
that eateth not, judge him that eateth.</hi> And <hi>ver. 14. Let
us not judge one another any more.</hi> Certainly this rule,
with ſuch others, reduced to practice, as are found in
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:159563:31"/>
their writings, would heale all. I ſhall not ſtand
to diſpute that place now. I ſhall onely upon
occaſion thereof, acquaint you with an Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
which to me was ſtrange (having conſidered for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
proceedings) when I firſt found it. In the late
<hi>Book of Canons</hi> that were made juſt afore this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
and ſtirs began, when the Biſhops would have
brought in <hi>bowing</hi> towards the Communion Table,
(the <hi>Altar,</hi> as it was called) after many ſpecious co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours
prefaced thereto, they cloſe all with this, <hi>In
the practice or omiſsion of this Rite, we deſire that the</hi>
RULE OF CHARITY <hi>preſcribed by</hi> THE APO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STLE
<hi>may be obſerved, which is, That they which uſe this
Rite,</hi> DESPISE NOT <hi>them who uſe it not; &amp; that they who
uſe it not,</hi> CONDEMNE NOT <hi>thoſe that uſe it.</hi> Could they
not have ſaid ſo ſooner? The obſerving this very rule
about thoſe other things urged by them, had ended
all the quarrels, prevented all the oppreſſions of ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
conſciences, that were during all their dayes;
it had ſaved and prevented the ſilencing of how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
faithfull Miniſters by them! But God, (who
who afore he puniſheth, uſually takes evidence, or at
leaſt layes a ground of their conviction whom he pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth)
when he had once drawne this out from
them, (though they did it for an end to facilitate the
introduction of that which was a novelty) yet then <hi>ex
ore tuo,</hi> out <hi>of their owne mouthes</hi> he condemnes them,
and ſtayes not a moment from the execution. But
from that time and word uttered by them and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed
to the world, began their ruine, it haſtned, and
haſtned inſtantly.</p>
               <p>I am confident of it, that Chriſt that <hi>King of Saints</hi>
that is in heaven, he will not reſt till ſuch time as hee
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:159563:32"/>
hath made us one, if not in judgement, yet in fobea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance;
and that if we will not take warning, and will
not agree it, that either <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> or <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi>
himſelfe will come in upon us, and we ſhall be made
to doe it one way or other.</p>
               <p>But if this great deſigne of reconciling all the
Saints could be brought to a full iſſue and perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:
and if this your Intereſt, (<hi>a regard had to all the
Saints in this Kingdome,</hi> which to me upon all the
grounds fore-mentioned is the greateſt Intereſt of
this Kingdome) be followed and maintained, I would
not feare, <hi>though</hi> (as the Prophet <hi>Zachary</hi> ſaith of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,
Chap. 3. ver.</hi> 3.) <hi>all the people of the earth were
gathered together againſt us.</hi> We feare forraigne For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces;
certainly let us keep to our <hi>owne proper Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt,</hi>
and then if all the Nations of the world were ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered
together againſt us, I beleeve they would have
the hardeſt pull of this Nation that ever was of any:
THE LORD IS HERE, (as the Prophet ſpeaks, <hi>Ezek.</hi>
35. 10.) or (let me expreſſe it in thoſe ſimilitudes <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chary</hi>
there uſeth) if they ſhould come, and think to
devoure us, they will find this Kingdome to be a <hi>cup
of poyſon</hi> to them, <hi>ver.</hi> 2. (ſo tis in your margents, but
we reade it, <hi>a cup of trembling</hi>) which they muſt not
onely vomit up againe, but will be their death and
deſtruction: they will finde it to be a <hi>burthenſome
ſtone,</hi> as <hi>ver.</hi> 3. which while they goe about to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne,
or ſtirre, or meddle withall, it ſhall fall back
upon them, and cut them to pieces. <hi>I will make Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem
a burthenſome ſtone for all people; all that burthen
themſelves with it ſhall be cut in pieces, though all the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
of the earth be gathered together againſt it.</hi> And <hi>you</hi>
that are the GOVERNORS OF JUDAH, (as at the 6. <hi>ver.</hi>)
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:159563:32"/>
ſhal be <hi>as an harth of fire among the wood, and a torch of fire
in a ſheafe;</hi> and all that oppoſe you and riſe up againſt
you ſhall be but as ſo many <hi>ſtrawes.</hi> Take a ſtack of
ſtraw, great for bulk and number, and lay it upon a
few coales of fire upon an hearth, and what will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
of them all? though they cover the fire a
while, yet they will ſoone be conſume I and burnt up.
Read the 6. <hi>ver. I will make</hi> (ſaith God) THE GOVER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NORS
<hi>of Judah like a harth of fire among the wood, and
like a torch of fire in a ſheafe, and they ſhall devoure all the
people round about, on the right hand and on the left.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhall onely end with what is further ſpoken there
of theſe Governours of <hi>Judah</hi> in the 5. <hi>verſe,</hi> (which
is the ſumme of what I have ſaid) THE GOVERNORS
OF <hi>Judah</hi> SHALL SAY IN THEIR HEARTS, (as
comforting themſelves thereby) <hi>The inhabitants of
Jeruſalem ſhall be my</hi> STRENGTH, <hi>in the Lord of Hoſts</hi>
THEIR GOD. And ſo ſay you, the <hi>Saints</hi> of this our
<hi>Jeruſalem</hi> are our greateſt INTEREST and ſecurity
through the <hi>Lord of Hoſts,</hi> his being <hi>our God:</hi> And let
this <hi>ſaying</hi> be ever in your hearts, to <hi>encourage</hi> and
to <hi>guide</hi> you.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="Parliamentary_order">
            <opener>
               <date>Die Mercurii 25. Feb. 1645.</date>
            </opener>
            <p>ORdered by the Commons aſſembled in Parliament, That Sir <hi>Robert Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley</hi>
and Maſter <hi>Purefoy</hi> doe from this Houſe give Thanks to Maſter
<hi>Thomas Goodwin</hi> for the great paines he took in the Sermon he preached
this day at the intreaty of this Houſe at S. <hi>Margarets</hi> Weſtminſter, (it being
the day of Publique Humiliation) And to deſire him to print his Sermon. And
it is Ordered, that none ſhall print his Sermon without licenſe under his hand
writing.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>H. Elſynge Cler. Parl. Dom. Com.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="appointment">
            <p>I doe appoint <hi>Robert Dawlman</hi> to print this Sermon.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Tho: Goodwin.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="Parliamentary_order">
            <pb facs="tcp:159563:33"/>
            <opener>
               <date>Die Mercurii, Febr. 25. 1645.</date>
            </opener>
            <p>ORdered by the Commons aſſembled in Parliament, that
S. <hi>Robert Harlow,</hi> and Col. <hi>Purfrey</hi> do give thanks to
M. <hi>Burgeſſe,</hi> and M. <hi>Goodwin,</hi> for the great pains they took
in the Sermons they preached this day, at the intreaty of the
Houſe of Commons, at S. <hi>Margarets</hi> Weſtminſter (it being the
day of publick Humiliation) and to deſire them to print their
Sermons. It is alſo ordered, That none ſhall preſume to
print their Sermons without licence under their hand-writing.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Hen. Elſ. Cler. Parl. D. Com.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="appointment">
            <p>I appoint <hi>Thomas Underhill</hi> to print my Sermon, and
no man elſe.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>ANTHONY BURGESSE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
